<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certayne Godly exarcises [sic] meditacions and prayers very necessary and profytable for all persons and for all times, set forthe by certayne godly lerned men, to be vsed dayly as you shalbe godly disposed, and shall feele nede thervnto. And also the letany dayly vsed in churches annexed to the ende hereof.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1565</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00481</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10617</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115579</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850797</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850797</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16024</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00481)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16024)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 566:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certayne Godly exarcises [sic] meditacions and prayers very necessary and profytable for all persons and for all times, set forthe by certayne godly lerned men, to be vsed dayly as you shalbe godly disposed, and shall feele nede thervnto. And also the letany dayly vsed in churches annexed to the ende hereof.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[128] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Fletestrete at the sygne of the George neere to saincte Dunstons churche by VVyllyam Powell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[ca. 1565]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Almost half of the selections are reprinted in STC 4028, 4029.5 and following, but not in the section called "Lydlyes prayers", a title W. Powell entered in 1562-63 and 1565-66--STC.</note>
                  <note>Suggested publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>CERTAYNE <hi>GODLY EXARCISES</hi> MEDITACIONS AND PRAYERS, VERY</hi> neceſſary and profytable for all perſons and for all times, ſet forthe by certayne godly lerned men, to be vſed dayly as you ſhalbe godly diſpoſed, and ſhall feele nede thervnto. And alſo the Letany dayly vſed in Churches annexed to the ende hereof.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Epheſians. vi. &amp;. i. Timothe. ii.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>¶ Praie alwaies euery where with all maner of praier, and that in the ſpirite, lifting vp pure hartes and handes, with out wrath or doubtinge.</p>
            </q>
            <p>¶ <hi>IMPRINTED. <hi>London in Fleteſtrete at the ſygne of the George neere to ſaincte Dunſtons churche by VVyllyam Powell.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:2"/>
            <p>¶ Vſe often and hartye prayer to God, knowing that it is no leſſe neceſſary for your ſoule therby to liue and contynue in godlines, then water is for the life of fiſhe, or dew is for the growth of graſſe and herbes: but if you wyll haue youre praier accepted of god, ſe that you accept his worde. For accurſed be they (ſayth Sallomon) and their prayer, that wyll not heare the worde of god. If I behold with fauour any wyckednes (ſaith Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid) in my hart, god will not heare me, for he heareth no ſuch ſynners as retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethe ſtyll the purpoſe to continewe it ſinne, as hee ſtoppethe not hys eares to heare the prayers of the pore penitents, but often before they pray he graunteth them their hartes deſire.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:2"/>
            <head>¶ Occations to meditate &amp; to ſtirre vp the harte to praier.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N your praiers thinke vpon the remiſſion of ſinnes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſed by and for Chryſte, and let there be in your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce ſome moſt eui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dente and playne ſentence to inflame &amp; ſtirre vp the mind, as this. Aſke and ye ſhal haue. &amp;c. And verely verely I ſaye vnto you, what ſoo euer you ſhall aſke the father in my name, he wyll geue it you. &amp;c. Aſking al ſpiritual gifts with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out condicion, and all temporall vppon condicion. As Chriſt did: Father if it be thy wyl let this cuppe paſſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="i."/> God commaundeth vs to aſke of him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="ii."/> We breake his commandment in not aſkynge.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="iii."/> We do his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement in aſking of hym.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="iiii."/> He promiſeth to vs our aſkinge.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="v."/> He is debtour to vs tyll he fulfill our aſkinge.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="vi."/> We make god a liar if we miſtruſt to obteine our aſkynge.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="vii."/> He is glorified in his ſonne by giuing
<pb facs="tcp:16024:3"/>vs our aſkynge.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="viii."/> He longeth to haue vs aſke of him, &amp; loketh for it at our handes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="ix."/> If we therfore turne not oure eares from his lawe, but call vpon him wyth a ſtronge Faythe, he will moſte gladly geue vs our aſkynge.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="x."/> Becauſe we are necligent in aſkinge he doth of his fatherly goodneſſe by ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities and troubles, dryue &amp; prouoke vs to aſke of hym.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xi."/> And becauſe we are ignoraunt in aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge, he teacheth vs by his holy ſpirite ſent into our hartes, and by the prayer that therfore is called the lordes praier how &amp; what we ſhulde aſke of him.</p>
            <p>Let vs therefore in our neceſſitie and troubles, aſke of god our father and he for his ſonnes ſake will geue vs our aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge, whoſe very nature and propertie is to relieue ſuche as are in neceſſitie, and in deede our neceſſities are as lowde cryinges in his merciful eares.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:3"/>
            <head>A meditation vpon the Lordes prayer.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Q</seg>Vr father which art in heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We gloriouſely formed vnto the Image of thy deuine maieſtie, created by thy gracyouſe good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vnto higheſt honour, how be it by our own ſinfulnes diffigured with vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes deſeruinge dampnation, and yet by Chriſtes death redemed and reſtored vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to grace to be Citizens with ſainctes of the family of God: Nowe altogether in Chriſtian vnitie as members of one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, we pray, deſyre, and truſt to obtayne of thee our heauenly father, accordinge vnto thy gracious goodnes mighty pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er, and faithefull promiſe, vnto vs that aſke, aboundaunce of thy grace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That, thy name may be halowed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That thy diuine power, and glorious maieſty, may be certainely knowne and reuerently honoured. That the hartes of vs men by thy word and prayer maye
<pb facs="tcp:16024:4"/>be ſanctified from all ſinne and vanity, ſo that we with al that we haue ſeruing thee in holineſſe &amp; righteouſeneſſe, may ſo ſhine afore men vpon earth, that they therby may be occaſion to honoure thee our father which art in heauen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thy kyngdome come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thy worde be ſo fruitfully preached amongeſt vs thy peple, that we may be throughly inſtructed &amp; taught to brydle our ſenſual apetites by natural reaſon, and to ſubmit our wyttes &amp; reaſons vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a good godly ſpirite, and to trye our ſpirites by the true ſcriptures. So that within vs may raigne the kingdome of God, which is neither meate nor drink whiche is neither ſuperſticious ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, voluptuous pleaſures, nor vayne glory, but righteouſnes, peace, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte in the holy ghoſt, by the which we now taſting of thy heauenly ioyes, may be made fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> henceforth wery of al world<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly vanities, continually loking &amp; pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge for the apperance and comming of thy eternall and euerlaſting kyngdom.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thy wyll be done in earth, as it is in heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In heauen the angelles of reuerente loue do thy will and commaundement, with comfortable courage &amp; ioyful plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure. In hel the wicked ſpirits through malice and enuye, repininge and grud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, do torment and vexe them ſelues, what ſo euer they be doinge. And vpon earth, men being ſubiect vnto ſinne, do thinke it a labour and paine, to be occu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pied in any thing that is good and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Wherfore we pray that the grace of thy heauenly ſpirite, maye ſo worke in our earthly bodies, that we being dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from ſinne and vanitie, may frely delite and take pleaſure to do thye wyll and commaundement, being men vpon earth, as thy glorious aungels do whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che be in heauen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Geue vs this day our dayly breade.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We hauinge great nede, not hable of our ſelues to deſerue any thing, beſeche the of thy fatherly goodnes, to geue fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto all vs in general: So that none be hurt nor hindered ſeuerally this day
<pb facs="tcp:16024:5"/>when as we crye conſtrained by preſent nede, not craftely crauing for vayn care againſt to morow, our dayly bread, our daily and neceſſarie foode &amp; reliefe, both bodely and ghoſtly. And eſpecially ſo: that the ſpiritual foode of Chriſtes fleſh and his bloud, by dayely preachinge of the goſpell, and miniſtracion of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes, maye repleniſhe our hartes &amp; mindes with continual remembrance of Chriſtes deathe, and his paſſion, day<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to be vſed for neceſſary and ſpirituall conſolation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Forgeue vs oure treſpaſſes, as we forgeue them that treſpas againſt vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Geue vnto vs that feling and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing oure owne ſynfulneſſe, do nede, and deſire thy mercifull forgeuenes of oure fautes &amp; treſpaſſes, which we haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt thee, ſo that we frely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geuing all other, that haue offended vs in any thyng what ſo euer it be, may be ſure that mercy ſpringyng in thee hathe proceded vnto vs, and being graciouſely offred of thee, hath ben thankefully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued of vs, and beinge charitably vſed of vs towardes other, ſhal moſt certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:16024:5"/>be confirmed and enlarged of thee to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vs: So that by free mercy ſpryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging and proceding from thee, al fautes maye be freely forgeuen: euen as thoſe which other hath committed againſt vs, ſo likewiſe thoſe whych we haue done a gainſt thee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And leade vs not into temptation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Suffer not the deuyll by the abuſe of thy benefites, to leade vs captyues into deceitefull and dampnable temptation, drawing vs by deinty meates, vnto gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy glotony, by money and richeſſe, vnto vnſaciable couetouſenes, and by wealth and proſperity, vnto pryde &amp; vayne glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and by al thy godly gracious giftes, vnto euery dyueliſhe abominable ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But deliuer vs from euill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Deliuer our goodes from abuſe, our bodies from corruption, our ſoules from damnation. Deliuer vs by Chriſt Ieſu, from the bondage of ſinne, vnto the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertye of the Goſpell, ſo that from all daunger of diueliſhe temptation, tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and enticing men toward damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we maye be deliuered to ſerue thee
<pb facs="tcp:16024:6"/>in holineſſe and ryghteouſeneſſe all the daies of our life, with moſt certaine and ſure hope of euerlaſting ſaluation, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Chriſt Ieſu, in whom our hope and thy promiſe is moſte certaine, that is to ſay. Amen.</p>
            <p>Your time is ſhort, your daungers be great: you are well warned by Goddes worde written. <hi>Mar. xiij. Take hede, watche, and praye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Take hede, that your hartes and min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des be not made heauy, hard, and dull, with meates and drink, vaine pleſures, or worldly cares.</p>
            <p>Watch, with dyllygence to doe youre owne dewties, in deſyrous lokynge for Chryſtes comming.</p>
            <p>Praye, that ye may eſcape all daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and ſtande in grace and fauoure afore the face of Chriſt, at his comminge.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. Leuer.</signed>
            </closer>
            <argument>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>APOCAL. XXII.</hi>
                  </bibl> 
                  <hi>Beholde I come ſone.</hi>
               </q>
            </argument>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:6"/>
            <head>¶ A prayer to be ſayde in the mornynge.</head>
            <p>O Almighty and moſte gracyous God, we hartely thancke thee for the ſwete ſlepe &amp; comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reſt whiche thou haſt geuen vs this nighte, and for as muche as thou haſte commaunded by thy holy worde that no man ſhoulde be idle, but all occupied in godly and vertuous exerciſes, euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> according to his calling, we moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeche thee that thine eies may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende vpon vs, dayely defende vs, che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe, comforte, and gouerne vs, and al our counſayles ſtudies and labours, in ſuche wiſe, that we maye ſpend and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowe this day accordynge to thy moſte holy wyll, without the hurtynge of our neighbours, and that we may diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye and warely eſchewe and auoyde all thinges that ſhoulde diſpleaſe thee, ſet thee alwaies before our eies, liue in thy feare, workyng that may be founde acceptable before thy diuyne maieſtie, through Ieſus Chriſt our lord. So be it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:7"/>
            <head>¶ A Confeſſion of our ſynnes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Mercifull and moſt louing fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whoſe Loue is infinite, whoſe mercye endureth for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, we ſinfull creatures tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinge in thine vnſpeakeable goodnes &amp; loue towardes vs, do appere this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge before thy dyuyne maieſtie, moſt humbly confeſſing our manifold ſinnes and innumerable tranſgreſſions of thy commaundementes and fatherly wyll: againſt thee only, againſt thee O lord, haue we ſynned. we acknowledge oure offences, we accuſe our ſelues vnto the O mercifull lord, and wyl not hyde our vnrighteouſneſſe, we fynde in our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues nothinge but ingnoraunce of thye wyll and diſobedience, miſtruſt, doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes in thy goodnes and incredulitie, hatred &amp; contempt of all ſpirituall thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, ſelfe loue, confidence in our ſelues, and feruent luſtinge after carnall thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of this worlde: and this tree of our corrupt nature, bryngeth forth continu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ally in vs, none other fruictes, but rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and vnſauery workes of the fleſhe, in thoughtes wordes and doinges vnto
<pb facs="tcp:16024:7"/>condempnation. Wherfore we humbly beſeche thy fatherly goodnes, euen for thy ſonne Ieſus Chriſtes ſake (whome thou haſt ſet forth for a purchaſer of mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cye vnto vs through fayth in hys bloud) make our hartes cleane, take away our ſtony hartes, and geue vnto vs a true &amp; a liuely fayth, whych ſhal worcke con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually by loue throughe Chriſt, haue mercy vppon vs, forgeue vs our ſinnes for thy ſonnes ſake, certifye our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of remiſſion of the ſame by thy ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſpirite, by whoſe operation ſo morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye in vs, our olde man, the whole body of ſinne, that we continually dyeng vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to ſinne, may walke in newneſſe of life to the glory of thy holy name, through Ieſus Chriſt our Sauiour. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:8"/>
            <head>¶ Before thou prayeſt, beleue that god is not onely almighty to helpe and to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyuer thee: but alſo that he is gracious and faythefull to fulfill all his promiſes made vnto vs. Then forgeue if thou haſt any thing againſt any man, And remember that thou com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meſt not to god with a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble harte, but lyfte vp pure handes with oute wrathe or doubtinge.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Almighty eternal &amp; euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuing god.<note place="margin">1. 2. <hi>Corin.</hi> 1. <hi>and.</hi> 2.</note>
               <hi>1.</hi> the eternal father of our Lorde Ieſus Chryſt whych haſte made <hi>2.</hi> heauen and yearthe,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Ictes.</hi> 4.</note> the ſea, and al that therin is, and of thy great goodnes, didſt open thy ſelfe from heauen, &amp; madeſt proclamatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Ieſus chriſt, ſaieng. <hi>3</hi> this is my deare ſonne heare him,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.</note> thou maker of al thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, preſeruer &amp; helper,<note place="margin">4. <hi>Philip.</hi> 2. <hi>Ebre.</hi> 1.</note> with thy. <hi>4.</hi> coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal ſonne our lord Ieſus Chriſt raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng with thee, and manifeſted in Ieru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſalem, and thy holy ghoſt poured on the apoſtles, O moſt wiſe, good, mercifull,
<pb facs="tcp:16024:8"/>righteous iudge, and alſo ſtrong, which haſt ſayde by thy prophet.<note place="margin">5. <hi>Ezechi.</hi> 18.</note>
               <hi>5.</hi> I will not the death of a ſinner, but that he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uert and liue: I thy pore creature and worke of thy handes, do acknowledge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe vnto thee my manifold ſynnes and offences, which I from my youth vp vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to this time, haue greuouſly committed againſt thee, in thought, worde, &amp; dede, &amp; am now taught &amp; moued by thy word &amp; grace, to be hartely ſory for the ſame, deſiring thee (which haſt ſayd.<note place="margin">6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.</note>
               <hi>6.</hi> call v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon me in the day of thy trouble, and I wyll heare thee, and delyuer thee) for the precious bloudde ſheading of Ieſus Chriſt thy ſonnes ſake our lord, whom thou wouldeſt to be made a ſlaine.<note place="margin">7. <hi>Eb.</hi> 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.10</note>
               <hi>7.</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for our ſinnes, to haue mercy vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon mee, and forgeue me all thoſe myne offences according to thy great mercy &amp; promiſe, whych haſte ſayde.<note place="margin">8. <hi>Eze.</hi> 18.</note>
               <hi>8.</hi> at what time ſo euer a ſinner doth repent him of his ſinne from the bottom of his hart, I will put al his wickednes out of my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce. O lorde I acknowledge and confeſſe that I was borne in ſinne,<note place="margin">9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.</note> and. <hi>9.</hi> conceiued in wickednes, and am by nature a. <hi>9.</hi> childe of wrath, for that
<pb facs="tcp:16024:9"/>in my. <hi>9.</hi> fleſhe (as ſaincte Paule ſaith) dwelleth no good thing, and that of my ſelfe I am not able to think a good. <hi>10.</hi> thought that can pleaſe thee,<note place="margin">10.2. <hi>Corin.</hi> 3.</note> much leſſe to wiſhe, and leaſt of al to doe that thou in thy lawe requireſte of me to be done, for.<note place="margin">11. <hi>Gala.</hi> 3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.</note>
               <hi>11.</hi> thou haſt ſaide, curſed is he that continuethe not in all thynges that are written in the lawe to do them: againe, thy lawe is. <hi>11.</hi> ſpiritual, but I am car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, ſolde vnder ſinne: therfore o lorde I call vnto thee for grace (whyche haſte ſaide.<note place="margin">12. <hi>Math.</hi> 7.</note>
               <hi>12.</hi> aſke and ye ſhall haue, ſeeke &amp; ye ſhall finde, knocke, and it ſhalbe ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto you) to preuent and drawe my will to all goodnes, (for none can come to thee,<note place="margin">13. <hi>Iho.</hi> 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.6</note> except he be drawne. <hi>13.</hi> againe excepte we be borne from aboue we can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not ſee the kingdome of god) aſſiſte ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore and gyde me alſo with thy holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite from time to time, drawe me there fore and I ſhall runne after thee, &amp; geue me ſtrength and ablenes through chriſte our lorde to accomplyſhe and fulfill the ſame,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Canti.</hi> 1.</note> lorde make me to become poore in ſpirite, vile and lowe in my owne ſight, that I lift not vp my ſelf aboue my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ihon.</hi> 1.</note> but that I eſteme my ſelfe to be
<pb facs="tcp:16024:9"/>as a ſeruaunt to al men to do the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good, after the example of chriſte, which came not to be miniſtred vnto but to miniſter, for he hathe ſayde.<note place="margin">14. <hi>Math</hi> 5. <hi>Iames.</hi> 4.</note>
               <hi>14.</hi> Bleſſed are the pore in ſpirite: againe, thou reſiſteſt the <hi>14.</hi> proud, but geueſt grace to the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, geue mee therefore thy grace, that when ſo euer I be ouer taken wyth any kinde of ſynne and wickednes eyther in thought, word, or dede, or that I fele my owne infirmitie or weakeneſſe, I maye immediatly with harty repentaunce.<note place="margin">15. 2. <hi>Timo.</hi> 2</note>
               <hi>15</hi> (which is alſo thy gyfte) returne to thee againe, and not to lie ſtil in the ſecurity of ſin. Take from me my ſtony, vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuing, blynd, doubtfull, vnfaithfull, &amp; vnthankeful hart, and. <hi>16.</hi> repoſe in me an hart of fleſhe, to bowe and encline to thy wil: my carnall, idle, ſecure, &amp; impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent hart, take away from me, &amp; geue me an hart to feare thee, to loue thee, to truſte in thee for euer, write thy lawe in my harte, graue it in my mynde, that I may beleue, truſt, and liue in thee ſor e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere. Deliuer me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſpirite of pryde and vaine glory, all hautines of minde, preſumption, ſelfe loue, and ſelfe truſt, that I ſtand not to hye in my owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyt,
<pb facs="tcp:16024:10"/>but that I may be willing rather to learne then to teach. Lake from me that wicked ſpirite of ſuſpicion and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy, euil gelouſy, vaine ſurmiſings, mur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>muring, and grudging, whiſpering, or backbiting of any, eſpecially ſuch as be in auctority, and miniſters of thy word. O lord kepe me from al wrath, malice, and haſtyneſſe, all reſpecte of perſonnes in the faith, all lying, euill wordes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, flatteryng, diſſimulation, I po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſy, blaſphemy, and vaine ſwering by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> name of god, his works, or creatures, from all lightnes, idle wordes, and all vnſtablenes of hart. O lord deliuer thou my hart from all filthyneſſe both of the fleſh and ſpirite, as hereſy, and errours, from al vncleane thoughtes and vnlau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deſires, euil concupiſence and luſtes of the body. Lake fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me alſo couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and mordinate care of riches, all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit and guile in my callinge and office, all idlenes and ſlouth, and geue me not ouer vnto an vnſhamefaſt and obſtinate mende. Make me able and contented to beare occaſions with pactence whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be offred or geuen me, and not to recom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pence euyll for euyll, neyther to ſwell,
<pb facs="tcp:16024:10"/>nor to murmure, nor to be ſolemne, nor angry. Good lord make me very loth to geue occaſions of euil to any man, &amp; if I chaunce to geue any, make me willyng to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe my fault &amp; to ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it. Graunt me grace y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I may be wylling and fre to geue, but loth to take &amp; receaue, becauſe it is more bleſſed to geue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to receiue. Geue me thy grace that I neuer enuye any good mans loue or woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, becauſe they do either loue god &amp; his peple more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I, or els that they be beloued of him or his more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I. make me to reioice in other mens gyftes, &amp; not to enuy them, becauſe they be better then mine, but ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther to geue thankes for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with al my hart, deſiring y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may be increſed in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; in me. Oh lord take fro me a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful hart in al worldly thinges, &amp; graunt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> neyther pouerty opreſſe me &amp; driue me to diſpatre or falſehod, nether riches lift me vp to forget thee or my ſelf, but that in proſperitie I may be thankefull, &amp; in aduerſitie pacient &amp; humble. Lord make me mery without lightnes, ſad without miſtruſte, ſober wythoute dulnes, true withoute doublenes, fearing thee, with out deſperation, truſting in the without
<pb facs="tcp:16024:11"/>preſumption: geue me alſo the ſpirite of humblenes, ſimplicitie, mekenes, gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlenes, goodnes, faithfulues, and truth, Braunt me O god the bowels of mercy and louing kindnes toward my brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, longe ſuffering &amp; pacience to beare al things well that thy prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhal ſe metee to lave vpon mee, regenerate my hart with the ſpirit of grace dayly more and more, geue me an inward taſte and feling of thy fauoure &amp; mercy towardes me in Chriſt Ieſu our lorde, that I may know thee to be my god and father, and my ſelfe to be thy chylde for euer more. Lorde mereaſe this my faith in thee and in chriſt thy ſonne my redemer, encreaſe and confyrine my hope in thy promyſes touchinge my ſaluation. Oh god make perfecte my loue toward thee and to my reademer and iuſtifier, geue me a trewe and vnfamed loue to al vertue &amp; godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and to all thy choſen people where ſo euer they be diſperſed throughout all the worlde, encreaſe in me ſtrength and victory againſt all temptations and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaultes of the fleſhe, the worlde, and the deuill,<note place="margin">18. 1. corin. 1</note> that accordinge to thy promiſe I be neuer further proued or tempted then
<pb facs="tcp:16024:11"/>thou wilt geue me ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth to ouercome. Geue me grace to kepe a good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, geue me a pure hart and minde, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue a right ſpirite within me, geue me alſo the true vnderſtandinge of thy holy worde, that I maye neuer ſwarue from the true ſenſe and meaning thereof, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my chefe felicitie may be in the ſame, in hearing, reading, talking, watching praying, faſting, mortifyinge, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duinge mine owne wyll and membres. O gracious lord Ieſus Chriſt, ſonne of the liuing god, which waſt. <hi>16.</hi> crucified and rayſed againe for vs,<note place="margin">10. Act. 2. &amp;. 3 20. Act. 2. &amp;. 7 21. Pſal. 68. Ephe. 4.22. 1. Timo. 2 1. Ihon. 2</note> which now ſit teſt and raigneſt on. <hi>20.</hi> the right hande of the father that thou mayſte. <hi>21.</hi> gyue giftes vnto men, and art apointed to be the onely. <hi>22.</hi> mediatoure and aduocate for vs vnto god, haue mercy vpon me, &amp; praye for me to thy eternall father, and ſanctify me with thy holy ghoſt, as thou haſt promiſed ſayinge, I will not leaue you. <hi>23.</hi> comfortleſſe, but will ſende you the ſpiryte of truthe whyche ſhall abyde with you for euer.<note place="margin">23. Ihon. 14.</note> Kindle my mind and hart with thy holye ſpirite, that I maye truely beleue in thee, acknowledge and call vpon thee, geue thankes and obeye
<pb facs="tcp:16024:12"/>thee, for I feele my ſelfe ſo clothed and cloyed with infirmities and ſynne, that I know not what to do, but euen to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vp my ſelfe wholy wyth all my cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and corrupte nature, ſo muche as it is in wyll and workes, vnto thy mercy to be corrected &amp; refourmed at thy owne wil and pleaſure. Moſt mighty god and father, through our lorde Ieſus Chryſte thy eternal ſonne, with thy holy ſpirite, gouerne and kepe thy holye catholyke &amp; apoſtolike church, &amp; euery me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of the ſame, as thou haſt promiſed ſaying, this is.<note place="margin">24. <hi>Eſai.</hi> 56.</note>
               <hi>24.</hi> my couenaut with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, my ſpirite which is in thee, and my word which I haue put in thy mouthe, ſhal not depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the mouth of thy ſede for euer, ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vs alwayes with thy goſpell, rule &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme our harts with thy ſpirite, leaſt the Ipocriſy &amp; ſuperſtition of papiſtes, &amp; other heretikes, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erroures &amp; wicked life of Epicures &amp; Lybertynes, cauſe vs to fal. Gouerne therfore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtudies of thy church, &amp; defend the policies of thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>almes &amp; cities which geue harborough to thy people,<note place="margin">25. <hi>Sacha.</hi> 12.</note>
               <hi>25.</hi> powre vppon vs the ſpirite of grace and prayer, make vs di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligente and happy in the workes of our
<pb facs="tcp:16024:12"/>vocation, take into thy cuſtody for euer our ſoules and bodies, our liues, and al that euer we haue. Be gracious and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable (O lord) to all Iewes, Turks, Infidels, heretikes, and euen oure very enemies, and according to thy good wil and purpoſe forgeue them their ſinnes. Conuert vnto thy truth all thoſe whom thou haſte apoynted in Ieſus Chryſte to ſaluation. Be merciful alſo (O lord) to all our bretherne and ſiſterne that ſuffer anye kynde of perſecutyon or affliction, whether in mynde or in body, eſpecially ſuch as ſuffer for thy name and goſpell, geue them pacience, conſtancy, and ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſte hope till thou ſende theym full and good deliueraunce of all their troubles. Be gracious to al thoſe whom thou haſt coupled and linked to vs in loue &amp; frend ſhippe, whoſe hartes thou haſt moued to praye for vs, to wyſſhe vs good, to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coure and helpe vs in oure neceſſytyes, graunt vs all thy bleſſing and holy ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, to ſanctify vs in the vnity of fayth, and dwel in vs for euer. Finally oh lord haue mercy vpon my wife, children, and famely, which thou haſt geuen me, and encreaſe thy feare in our hartes that we
<pb facs="tcp:16024:13"/>maye truely loue thee, and one of vs an other in thee, ſo that we maye be pure both in ſoule and body, and bryng them vp in vertue, nurture, and information of the lord. Plant and ſowe in my harte all vertues that be neceſſary and requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in a chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man, namely wiſdome, diſcretion, te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perance, pacience, ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, and boldenes, and geue me grace ſo to vſe them and all other giftes whyche I haue receaued at thy mercifull hand, as may be moſt to thy glory and praiſe, to my conſolatyon &amp; ſaluation, and to the profyte of thy Churche.<note place="margin">26. <hi>Eſai.</hi> 64.</note> which peticions and requeſtes I do not make (O Lorde) truſtinge in myne owne ryghteouſneſſe (which I do acknowledge with thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet to. <hi>29.</hi> be ſtayned &amp; defiled) no but onely in thy great mercye and promiſe. O heare me lord, forgeue me lorde, con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſider me, and tary not ouer long, but for thy owne ſake doe it, and for thy ſonne Ieſus Chryſtes ſake (in whome all thy promyſes are, yea and amen) whych is our onely reademer, ſauiour, and Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fier, to whom with thee o father and the holy ghoſt be al glory &amp; prayſe now and for euer. Amen. Lord let it be ſo.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Robart Coles</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:13"/>
            <head>A morninge prayer.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E humbly and hartely geue tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes to thee (O merciful father) in and by thy derely beloneb ſonne Ieſus Chriſt our only ſauiour, that to thy innumerable benefites hitherto powred vpon our ſoules and vpon oure bodies, thou haſt vouchedſafe to kepe vs al this night paſt, from many euils, ſpiritually and corporally, and nowe of thy mercye doeſt offer and geue vs time to repente, &amp; to amend our liues, ſo that we might lyue hence forth not as we will, but as thou wilte: and as our bodies do drawe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually nearer and nearer their end, (y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> graue I meane) ſo our ſoules myght aproche to theyr ende, that is, heauen &amp; not hel (For in one ſtate we ſtande not ſtyll, but eyther we are nearer &amp; nearer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> happy ſtate of life, or els y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> infortunat or vnhappy condicion of death eternall) Therefore we beſech the to be merciful vnto vs good father, that is wee praye thee, as of thy goodnes thou geueſte vs time to repente &amp; to liue godly, ſo of the ſame thy goodnes in chriſt, we humbly
<pb facs="tcp:16024:14"/>beſech and pray thee to geue vs thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious gift of true, holy, perfect and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perpetuall repentaunce, that we maye more and more lamente our former ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full life, truſting vnfainedly in thy rych mercye, throughe the merytes of Ieſus Chriſt, for the pardone of al onr ſinnes, and that we maye vnfainedly purpoſe &amp; effectually labour to amende our liues this day and ſo long as we haue to liue, in al our doinges and wordes, and euen in oure very thoughtes, to the praiſe of thy holye name, &amp; good example of our neyghboures and bretherne. And for as much as thou knoweſt our weakeneſſe, our ignoraunce, &amp; great vntowardneſſe to cary any geeat croſſe or affliction, we beſech thee oure ſwete father, ſo to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and order all thynges towardes vs this day and for euer, that we be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer further proued and tempted, then thou wilt ſo helpe vs in the ſame, as may be moſt to thy glory and our ſaluation, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough Ieſus Chryſte our lorde. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. Coles.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:14"/>
            <head>¶ An Euening praier.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſte mercyful God and ten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der Father, whiche beſides thyne ineſtimable mercyes declared &amp; geuen vnto vs in the making of the world for our ſakes, in redemynge of vs by the deathe of thy dere ſonne Ieſus Chriſte, in the callynge of vs to the knowledge of thy bleſſed worde, in keping of vs hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto in thy holy Catholike churche, &amp; in the moſte gracious gouerninge of vs and all thinges hitherto for our mooſte weale, haſt alſo moſt fatherly cared for vs, and kept vs this daye from all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers bothe of ſoule and body, geuing vs bealth, foode, apparell, &amp; al other thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges neceſſary for the comforte &amp; ſuccour of this poore &amp; miſerable lif, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other do want: for theſe and al other thy good giftes and gracious benefites, which thou of thine owne goodnes one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; fatherly prouydence, for Chriſtes ſake haſt hitherto powred vppon vs, &amp; doeſt preſently powre vpon vs, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other, wee moſt humbly thanke thee &amp; prayſe thy holy name, beſeching thee
<pb facs="tcp:16024:15"/>euen for the ſame thy Chriſt, to pardon our vnthanckefulnes, our neglectynge and abuſing of thoſe thy benefites, and all our ſinnes whiche this daye or any tyme heretofore we haue commytted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte thy holy commaundementes.</p>
            <p>And as nowe we purpoſe to lay our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes to reſt, ſo graunte the garde of thy good Aungelles to keepe the ſame this night and for euer. And where or when ſo euer our laſt ſlepe of death ſhal come, graunte that it may be in thee, good fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo that our bodies may reſte bothe temporally and eternally, to thy glory and our ioye, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde. So be it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R.C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>¶ Certaine exerciſes to meditate, very profitable to euery Chriſtian.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Atche and Pray,<note place="margin">Part. 4.</note> that ye en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not into temptation. &amp;c. For the deuyll your aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary goeth about lyke a roa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryng lion, ſeking who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he may deuoure.</p>
            <p>Committe thy ſelfe, and all thye do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges vnto god, with feruent and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full praier: and then doubte nothing at
<pb facs="tcp:16024:15"/>all of the good and profitable ſucceſſe of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Pray before thou comeſt into any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, that thou geue no offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in worde or dede, but rather mayſt geue good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aumple to edyfie.</p>
            <p>Pray alſo that thou mayſt marke wel and immitate that whiche is well done and ſpoken, and that thou maiſt forget and flie from that whiche is euyll doone or ſpoken of any one where thou ſhalte come.</p>
            <p>Pray when thou art come alone from company, with any that god wyl make them to forgette the euyll example thou haſt geuen in worde or dede.</p>
            <p>In euery prayer begge of god the ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of grace and prayer,<note place="margin">zacha. 12.</note> that thou maiſt haue delight in praier and talking with God, aſke (I ſay) continually his holy ſpirite with encreaſe of Faith &amp; Hope.</p>
            <p>In euery benefite behold goddes grace and ſtay not the conſidering of the ſame tyll thou comeſt to the oryginall &amp; rote, that is the grace of god in Chriſt, before the worlde was made: ſo ſhal euery be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite confirme thy Faith.</p>
            <p>Speake, thinke, and do al thinges as
<pb facs="tcp:16024:16"/>in the ſight of god, and as vnto god.</p>
            <p>Of all thy thoughtes,<note place="margin">Eccle. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> woordes, and dedes, conſider the ende: and thou ſhalt neuer do amiſſe.</p>
            <p>Truſt in god whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou feleſt no cauſe in thy ſelfe: for that is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greteſt honour thou canſt geue vnto him, and a ſure to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken that thou arte his Chylde for euer.</p>
            <p>When thou beholdeſt any of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of god, beware thou do it not to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehende him, for ſo thou looſeſt thy la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: but loke vpon theym, to beholde him to be a God of might and power, in the diuerſitie of theym to be exceadynge wiſe, by the multitude of theym, to be good and gracious, whiche hath ſo done them that they ought to be had in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of vs: And when thou haſt this profite by them, then be thou thanckful to god who hath geuen it thee.</p>
            <p>The more ſure we are of our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; that we be the children of god, the tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples of the holy ghoſt, &amp; the inherytours of heauen, the more we cannot but loue &amp; long for the diſſolutions of our bodies. Vſe therfore to beg of god by continual praicr his ſpirite to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme you in this certen perſwaſion that god loueth you.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:16"/>
            <p>In the lawe behold god to be thy god, to be holy, to be iuſt, and ſeuere againſt ſynne: and thy ſelfe vnholy, vniuſt, and full of contumacie, &amp; therfore not mete, nor worthy, to be where god is: but to be reiected fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, and worthy damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, &amp; therfore feare him &amp; ſinne not.</p>
            <p>In the goſpell beholde god to be thye father, to loue the euerlaſtingely, to for geue thee all thy ſynnes, to geue thee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ſaluation through his ſonne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte, who hath ouercome ſinne, death, and hell, for thee, &amp; hath brought lyfe &amp; ymmortalitie vnto light: &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore loue him as a ſon, loue hym, for he loued thee fyrſt, loue hym (I ſay) in and for his Chriſt, loue his Chriſt, loue him euer: Onely beleue in him, forget not to be thanckefull to hym, for that he is thy god, and thy father, for his loue, for his Chriſt, for thy ſaluation, for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of thy ſynnes, for thy delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce from diſpaire, for the ſure certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficate of thyne election, for the delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce from errour into his truthe, for calling the into this grace wherin thou ſtandeſt: and therfore reioyce in hope of the glory of God.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. Coles</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:17"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Complaynt of the Tiranny vſed</hi> againſt the ſainctes of god, contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a confeſſion of our ſinnes, &amp; a praier for the deliuerance and preſeruation of the Church, and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes. **</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ternall and euerlyuinge god, father of our lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, who haſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded vs to praye, and promiſed to heare vs, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> when we do call from the pyt of deſperation: the miſeries of theſe our moſte wycked dayes compell vs, to poure forth before thee, the complaintes of our wretched hartes, oppreſſed wyth ſorrowe. Our eyes do beholde, and our eares do heare the calamities and opreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions whiche no tongue canne expreſſe, neyther yet (alas) doo oure dull hartes rightly conſider the ſame. For the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then are entred into thine inherytance, they haue poluted thy ſanctuarye, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaned and aboliſhed thy bleſſed inſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, moſte cruelly murthered, and
<pb facs="tcp:16024:17"/>dayly doe murther thy deare children.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt exalted the arme and force of our enemies, thou haſt ſet vs forth as a praye, to ignomy and ſhame, before ſuch as perſecute thy truth. Their wayes do proſper, they glory in miſchefe, &amp; ſpeake prowdely agaynſte the honoure of thy name.</p>
            <p>Thou goeſt not forth as a captaine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our hoſtes. The edge of our ſword, which ſomtime was moſt ſharp, is now blunt, and doth returne without victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye in battaile.</p>
            <p>It apereth to our ennemies (O lorde) that thou haſt broken that league, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of mercie &amp; goodnes, thou haſt made with thy churche. For the libertie whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che they haue to kil thi childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> like ſhepe and to ſhed their bloudde, no man reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinge, doth ſoo blynde and puffe theim with pride, that they ar not aſhamed to affirme, that thou regardeſt not our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treatinge. Thy longe ſuffering and pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cience maketh them hold from crueltie, to procede to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blaſphemy of thy name.</p>
            <p>And in this meane ſeaſon (alas) we do not conſider the heauines of our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which longe haue deſerued at thye
<pb facs="tcp:16024:18"/>handes, not onely theſe temporall pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues: but alſo the tormentes prepared for the inobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. For we knowing thy bleſſed will, haue not applyed our dily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to obey the ſame, but haue folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed for the moſt parte, the vaine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation of the blind world: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in very iuſtice haſt thou viſited our vnthanckfulneſſe. But O lorde if thou ſhalt obſerue and kepe in mind for euer the iniquities of thy children, then ſhal no fleſhe abide, nor be ſaued in thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. And therfore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uicted in our own conſciences, that moſt iuſtly we ſuffer, as puniſhed by thy hande, do neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe cal for mercy, according to thy pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes. And firſt we deſire to be corrected, with the rod of thy children, by the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che we maye be brought to a perfect ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of ſynne, and of our ſelues: &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore that it would pleaſe thee, for Chriſt Ieſus thy ſonnes ſake, to ſhewe to us &amp; thy whole church vniuerſally perſecuted the ſame fauoure and grace, that ſome times thou diddeſt, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the chiefe mem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bers of the ſame, for anguiſh and feare, were compelled to cry: why haue nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons raged? why hathe the people made
<pb facs="tcp:16024:18"/>vprores? and why haue princes &amp; kings coniured againſt thyne anointed, Chriſt Ieſus? Then diddeſt thou wonderfully aſſiſte and preſerue thy ſmale and diſper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed flock: then diddeſt thou burſte vp the barres, and gates of yron: then dyddeſt thou ſhake the foundations of ſtronge pryſons: then dyddeſte thou plague the cruell perſecutours: &amp; then gaueſt thou ſome tranquilitie and reſt after thoſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng ſtormes and cruell afflictions.</p>
            <p>O Lord, thou remaineſt one for euer: we haue offended, and are vnworthy of any deliueraunce, but worthy art thou to be a true and conſtant god, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy is thy deare ſonne Chriſt Ieſus, that thou ſhouldeſt glorify his name, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueng the blaſphemy ſpoken againſt the truth of his goſpell, which is by our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries damned as a doctrine deceiua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; falſe: yea, the bloude of thy ſonne is troden vnder fete, in that the bloud of his members is ſhedde for wytneſſyngs of thy truth. And therefore, O lorde, beholde not the vnworthines of vs, that call for the redreſſe of theſe enormities, neither let our imperfections ſtoppe thy mercies from vs, but beholde the face of
<pb facs="tcp:16024:19"/>thyne annointed Chriſte Ieſus, and let the equitie of oure cauſe preuayle in thy preſence. Let the bloudde of thy ſainctes which is ſhed, be openly reuenged in the eyes of thy Churche: that mortall men may know the vanity of their counſels, and that thy children may haue a taſt of thine eternal goodneſſe. And ſeing that from that man of ſinne, that Romayne Antechriſte, the chyefe aduerſary of thy deare ſonne, do the all iniquitie ſpringe, and myſchyefe procede: let it pleaſe thy fatherly mercy, more and more to reuele his deceit and tiranny to the worlde: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the eies of princes and magiſtrates, that clearely they may ſee, how ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullye they haue bene, and are abuſed by his deceiuable wayes, how by him they are compelled moſt cruelly to ſhede the bloud of thy ſainctes, and by viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe thine eternall teſtament: that they in depe conſideration of their greuous offences, maye vnfaynedly lament their horrible defectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from Chriſt Ieſus thy ſonne, from henceforth ſtudieng to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote his glorye in the dominions com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to their charges, that ſo yet once againe the glory of thy goſpell may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears
<pb facs="tcp:16024:19"/>to the worlde. And ſeing alſo that the chiefe ſtrength of that odious beaſte conſiſteth in defenſion of princes: let it pleaſe thee, O father, whiche haſt clay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to thy ſelfe to be called the God of peace, to vnite and knyt in perfect loue, the hartes of all thoſe that looke for the life euerlaſtinge. Let no craft of ſathan moue them to warre one againſte an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, neither yet to mainteine by their force and ſtrengthe, that kingedome of darkeneſſe, but rather that godly they may conſpire (illuminated by thy word) to roote out from amongeſt them, al ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſticion with the maynteyners of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Theſe thy graces, O lord, we vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly deſyre to be powred forth vppon all realmes and nations, that they may be firmly vnited and godly knitte toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the vnitie of thy worde: that in their godly concorde, thy name maye be glorified, and thy diſperſed flocke com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted and relieued.</p>
            <p>The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealthes, O lord, where thy goſpell is truely preached, and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borowe graunted to the afflicted mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſtes body, and ſpecially ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinge
<pb facs="tcp:16024:20"/>to our bounden duetie this out countrey of Englande, we commend to thy protection and mercy. Be thou vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them a defence &amp; buckler: be a watch man to their walles, &amp; a perpetual ſaue garde to their cities, that the crafty aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaultes of their ennemies repulſed by thy power, thy goſpell maye haue free paſſage from one nation to an other: &amp; let al preachers &amp; miniſters of the ſame haue the giftes of thy holy ſpirite, in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che aboundance, as thy godly wiſedome ſhal know to be expedient for the perfect inſtruction of that flocke, whiche thou haſt redemed with the preciouſe bloud of thy onely and welbeloued ſonne Ieſus Chriſt. Purge their hartes from al kind of ſuperſtition, from ambicion &amp; vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory, by whiche ſathan continually la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boureth to ſtirre vp vngodly conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cion, and let them ſo conſente in the vnitie of thy truthe, that neither the eſtimation whiche they haue of men, neyther the vaine opinions, whiche they haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued by their writinges, preuaile in them, againſt the cleare vnderſtandyng of thy bleſſed worde.</p>
            <p>And nowe laſt, O lorde, we moſt hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb facs="tcp:16024:20"/>beſeche thee, according to that prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of thy dere ſonne our lord Ieſus, ſo to ſanctifie and confirme vs in thy eternal veritie, that neither the loue of life tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, neither yet the feare of tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and corporall death, cauſe vs to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie the ſame, when the confeſſion of our faith ſhal be required of vs: but ſo aſſiſt vs with the power of thye holy ſpyrite, that not onely boldely we may confeſſe thee (O father of mercies) to be the true god alone, and who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haſte ſent our lord Ieſus to be the only ſauiour of the world: but alſo that conſtantly we may withſtande all doctrine, repugninge to thy eternall truthe, reueiled to vs in thy moſt bleſſed worde.</p>
            <p>Remoue from our hartes, the blynde loue of our ſelues, and ſo rule thou all the actions of our life, that in vs thye godly name may be glorified, thy chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che edified, and ſathan finally confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the power &amp; meanes of our lorde Ieſus Chriſte: to whom with thee, and the holy ſpirite, be all glory and prayſe before thy congregations, nowe and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. So be it.</p>
            <p>Ariſe, O lord, and let thine ennemies
<pb facs="tcp:16024:21"/>be aſhamed: let them flee from thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, that hate thy godly name: let the grones of thy priſoners enter in before thee, and preſerue by thy power, ſuche as be appointed to death: let not thyne enemies thus triumphe to the ende: but let them vnderſtande, that againſt thee they fight: preſerue and defend the vine, whiche thy righte hande hath planted: &amp; let all nations ſee the glory of thine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted.</p>
            <p>Haſten lord and tary not.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>A praier againſt the obſtinate enemies of the truth.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſte righteous iudge, god of all mercy and comforte, whiche by thy ſecrete iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente and wiſedome, doeſt ſuffer the wicked to triumph and increaſe for a tyme, for triall of the faith of thy welbeloued little flocke, and the mortifyinge of theyr luſtes, but at length to the vtter confuſion of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, &amp; ioyfull delineraunce of thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: loke doune we beſeche thee on thy
<pb facs="tcp:16024:21"/>diſperſed ſhepe, out of thy holy habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in heuen, and ſtrengthen our weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes againſte their furyous rages, abate their pryde, aſſwage their malyce, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found their deuiſes, wherwith they lifte vp them ſelues againſt chriſt Ieſus thy ſonne our Lord and Sauiour, to deface his glory and ſet vp Antechriſt. We be not able of oure ſelues to thynke a good thought, much leſſe to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d againſt their aſſaultes, excepte thy vndeſerued grace and mighty arme defend and deliuer vs. Performe thy promiſes made to Iacob, and ſtoppe the mouthes of the curſed E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domites, call them to repentance whom thou haſt apointed to ſaluation: bringe home them that runne aſtraye, lyghten the blind, and teach the ignoraunt: for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geue al thoſe that wilfully &amp; obſtinately rebell not againſt thy holy will, let thy fearefull threatninges pearce our ſtony hartes, &amp; make vs tremble at thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes. Make the exaumples of theim whom thou haſte ouerthrowne in their owne deuiſes, as Cayn, Cham, Nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod, Eſau, Pharao, Saule, Achitophel, Iudas, &amp; ſuch other to be a warning for vs, that we ſet not vp our ſelues againſt
<pb facs="tcp:16024:22"/>thy holy wil: graunt free paſſage to thy holy word, that it may worke effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in vs the worcke of life &amp; bleſſed hope of our ſaluation, to the eternal praiſe of thy maieſtye, throughe our mediatoure Chriſt Ieſus, to whom wyth the father and the holy ghoſt thre perſons and one god, be praiſe and thankeſgeuing in all congregations world without ende. So be it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ia. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>¶ A prayer for the common peace and quietnes of our countrey, neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for this our tyme.</head>
            <p>MOſt mercifull god, which haſt cre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ated man after thyne owne lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to lyue thereafter in godly peace and concorde, take away all ſtrife and debate, not onely in priuate cauſes betwyxte man and man, but eſpecially betwixt realme and realme, cuntrey and cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey, douchſaf to pacify the troublous affections of worldly mens hartes, who inflamed by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpirite of diſcorde, labour to breake that godly knotte of peace and concorde, which moſt beſemeth thy elect ſeruauntes and deſciples to performe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:22"/>
            <p>Gide thou vs in the vnitie of thy ſpirite, that we maye in thee be of one mynde, aſwell in matters touching the truth of religion: as alſo outward &amp; ciuill, that all maner groundes of diſcorde and war being taken away, we may liue in holy peace &amp; quietnes to the aduauncement of thy glory, and the ſettyng forth &amp; ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding abrode of thy goſpell. Geue good ſucceſſe (O Lorde) to the trauayles and counſailes of our gouernoures, directed to the ſafety &amp; quietnes of this realme.</p>
            <p>Defend and aide the miniſters, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailers about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. Bryng to naught all the ſubtill deuiſes of Sathan, of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techriſt and his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, deuiſed againſte the veritie of thy word, ouerthrow their counſailes, and bring their conſpiracye to naught, beate backe their proud bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in aduancing lies, and ſuppreſſing of the truth, and ſo make an ende at laſt of their outragious tiranny, that we thy ſeruauntes may quietly conſent and reſt in thy truth, hauinge both the inwarde peace of minde and conſcience, &amp; alſo the outward concorde aſwell amongeſt our ſelues, as wyth all forren natyons and cuntreis: graunt this O lord, for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:23"/>
            <head>¶ A praier for the whole church of chriſt. and for euery ſtate and degree therof accordinge to the petitions of the Lordes prayer ⸫</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lmighty god our heauenly Father, ſince thou haſt pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſed graciouſlye to heare vs and graunte our reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, whiche we ſhal make vnto the in the name of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt thy welbeloued ſon:<note place="margin">Ihon. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> And we alſo are taught by him and his apoſtelles to make our common prayer in his name, promiſyng that he wyl be amonge vs,<note place="margin">Math. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> and make interceſſion for vs vnto thee, for the obteinynge of all ſuche thinges as wee ſhall godly deſyre here in earth: And moreouer ſince thou haſt commaunded vs to pray for ſuch as thou haſt appoynted rulers, and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours ouer vs,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Timo.</hi> 2.</note> and alſo for all thynges nedefull for thy people: we therfore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauinge boldneſſe throughe thy holy worde; and leaninge aſſuredly vnto thy moſt vndoubted promiſes, do make our earneſt ſuplication vnto thee our moſte mercifull god, &amp; bountifull father, that for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake our onely ſauy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb facs="tcp:16024:23"/>and mediatour, it would pleaſe thee of thy infinite mercye, freely to pardon our offences, and in ſuche ſorte to draw and lifte vppe our hartes and affections towardes thee, that our requeſtes maye bothe procede of a feruent mynde, and alſo be agreable vnto thy moſte bleſſed wyll and pleaſure.</p>
            <p>We beſeche thee therfore (O heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father) as towchinge all princes and rulers, vnto whom thou haſt commyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the adminiſtration of thy iuſtice, and namely as towchinge the eſtate of oure moſte gracious Queene, that it woulde pleaſe thee to endue her and all her ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Counſaile with thy plentiful grace and principal ſpirite, and increaſe the ſame from time to time in her, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e may with a pure faith acknowledge Ieſus Chriſt thy onely ſonne our lorde, to be the kynge of all kynges,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Timo.</hi> 6. <hi>Act.</hi> 17. <hi>Math.</hi> 28.</note> and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of al gouernours, euen as thou haſt geuen al power vnto hym bothe in heauen and in earthe, and may vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and zelouſly ſeke and earneſtly mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine thy true glory, miniſter iuſtice, pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſhe ſynne, and defende the ryght, ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge her ſubiectes whiche be thy crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb facs="tcp:16024:24"/>and the ſhepe of thy paſture, euen as ſhe is taughte and commaunded by thy worde.</p>
            <p>We beſeche thee alſo (moſt deare fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) for al Paſtours and miniſters, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom thou haſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted the charge of mennes ſowles, and the miniſtery of thy holy goſpel, that it wold pleaſe thee ſo to guide theim with thy holy ſpirite, that they may be founde faythfull &amp; zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of thy glory, directing alwais their whole ſtudies vnto this ende, that the poore ſhepe which be gone aſtray out of the ſtocke, may be ſought out, &amp; brought againe vnto the lorde Ieſus (who is the chiefe ſhepeharde &amp; head of al Paſtours) wherby they may fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> day to day,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pe</hi> 5.</note> growe and increaſe in him vnto all righteouſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and holines. And on the other part, that it wolde pleaſe thee to delyuer thye churche from the daunger of ſuche idols ſhepehardes,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>che. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> wulues, and hirelynges, as ſeeke them ſelues and their bellyes, and not the ſettinge forthe of thy glorye and the ſafegarde of thy flocke.</p>
            <p>Moreouer we make our prayers vnto thee (moſt mercyfull father) for all men in general, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> as thou wilt be known to
<pb facs="tcp:16024:24"/>be the ſauiour of all the world by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption purchaſed by thy onely ſonne Ieſus Chriſt: euen ſo ſuche as haue ben bytherto holden captiue in darckneſſe &amp; ignoraunce for lacke of the knowledge of thy goſpell, maye throughe the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching therof, and the cleare light of thy holy ſpirite, be broughte into the righte way of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is to knowledge that thou art only very god, and that he whom thou haſte ſent is Ieſus Chriſte.<note place="margin">Iu. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> Likewiſe that they whom thou haſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready indued with thy grace, and whoſe hart thou haſt lightened with the know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge of thy word, may continually en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in godlineſſe, and be plenteouſely enryched wyth ſpirytuall benefytes: ſo that we may altogether worſhippe thee both with hart and mouthe, and render due honour and ſeruice vnto thee accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.</p>
            <p>In like maner (O lord of al true com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte) we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend vnto thee in our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers all ſuch perſons, as thou haſt viſited and chaſtiſed, by thy croſſe and tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, all ſuch people, as thou haſt puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with peſtilence, warre, and famin, and all other perſons afflycted with po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty,
<pb facs="tcp:16024:25"/>impriſonment, ſickeneſſe, baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente, or any like bodely aduerſitie, or haſt otherwiſe troubled and afflycted in ſpirite, that it will pleaſe thee to make them perceaue thy fatherly affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: that is that theſe croſſes be nothinge ells, but fatherly chaſtiſinges for their amendment, to the intent that they ſhould vnfainedly turne vnto thee, that they cleauinge vnto thee, mays re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue ful comfort, and be deliuered from all maner of euill.</p>
            <p>Finally moſt deare father we beſeche thee to graunt, that we may knowledge truely without hipocriſie bowe miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a ſtate of perdition we are in by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and how worthely we procure vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our ſelues euerlaſtinge dampnation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> heapinge vp from time to time thy gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uous puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes towards vs, through oure wicked and ſynfull life, to the ende that ſeing there remayneth no ſparke of goodnes in our nature, and that ther is nothing in vs (as touching our firſt cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, and that which we receaue of our parentes) mete to inioye the heritage of gods kingedome, we may wholy render by oure ſelues with all oure hartes, and
<pb facs="tcp:16024:25"/>with an aſſured co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, vnto thy dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloued ſon Ieſu Chriſt our lord; our only ſauiour &amp; redemer, to the ende that he dwelling in vs may mortefy our olde man (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay) our ſinneful affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and that we may be regenerated into a more godly lyfe: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> wherby thy holy name (as it is worthy of all honoure) may be aduaunced and magnified through oute the world and in al places: ſo that thou hauing the tuicion and gouernaunce o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs, we may learne dayely more and more to humble and ſubmyt our ſelues vnto thy maieſtie, in ſuch ſort that thou maiſt be counted king and gouernour o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer al, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> guiding thy people with the ſcep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter of thy word, and by the vertue of thy holy ſpirite, to the confuſion of all thine enemies, through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mighte of thy truth &amp; righteouſnes: ſo that by this meanes all power and heighte which withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth thy glory, may be continually thro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen downe and abolyſhed, vnto ſuche time as the full and perfecte face of thy kingdome ſhall apeare when thou ſhalt ſhewe thy ſelfe in iudgement: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> whereby alſo we with the reſte of thye creatures may render vnto thee perfecte and due
<pb facs="tcp:16024:26"/>obedience, euen as thy holy aungells do apply them ſelues onely to the perfour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of thy commaundementes: ſo that onely thy will may be fulfilled without any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradiction, &amp; that euery man may bend him ſelfe to ſerue and pleaſe thee, renouncing their owne wylles with all the affections and deſires of the fleſhe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Graunte vs alſo good lorde, that wee thus walking in the loue and dreade of thy holye name, maye be nouryſhed and ſuſteyned through thy goodneſſe, &amp; that we may receue at thy handes, all things expediente &amp; neceſſary for vs, and ſo vſe thy giftes peaceably and quietly, to this ende that when wee ſee that thou haſte care of vs, wee maye the more affectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſely knowledge thee to be our father, lokinge for all good giftes at thy hand: and withdrawynge and pullinge back al our vaine confidence from creatures, may ſet it wholly vpon thee, and ſo reſt onely in thy moſt bountiful mercy. And for ſo moch as, whiles we continue here in this tranſitory life, we are ſo miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſo frayle, and ſo much inclyned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſynne, that we fall continually and ſwarue from the right way of thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes:
<pb facs="tcp:16024:26"/>we beſeche the pardon vs our innumerable offences, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> whereby we are in daunger of thy iudgemente &amp; condempnation, and forgeue vs ſo free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that deathe and ſynne may hereafter haue no title againſt vs: neither lay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our charge that wicked rote of ſinne, whiche dothe euermore remaine in vs: but graunt that we may forget and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geue the wronges whiche other do vnto vs, &amp; in ſtede of ſeking vengeaunce, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> may procure the wealthe of our ennemies.</p>
            <p>And for as muche as of our ſelues, wee are ſo weake that we ar not able to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vpright one minute of an houre: and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain ſo belaid &amp; aſſaulted euermore with ſuch a multitude of ſo dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, that the deuyl, the world, ſynne &amp; our own co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cupice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, do neuer leaue of to fyghte againſt vs, Let it be thy good pleaſure to ſtrengthen vs with thy holy ſpirit, &amp; to arme vs with thy grace, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> that therby we may be able ſtrongly to with ſtand al te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptations, &amp; to endure conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this ſpiritual battaile againſt ſyn, vntil ſuch time as we ſhal obteine y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ful victory, &amp; ſo at length may triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ioyſe in thy kingdome with our captain &amp; gouernour Ieſus chriſt our lord. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:27"/>
            <q>
               <p>Who can tel whether the lord wil turne againe and haue compaſſion vpon vs, and leaue a bleſſinge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hynde him.</p>
               <bibl>Ioel. <hi>2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>¶ A prayer mete for this preſent tyme, that god woulde turne away his plagues hanging ouer vs for our ſinnes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>H lorde God, ſtrong and mighty, great and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, whiche dwelleſt in the heauens, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt great wonders, we thy myſerable chyldren here vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth, do moſt humbly beſeche thee to be mercifull vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, to pardon our offences, &amp; forgers vs all our ſinnes. O Lord enter not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to iudgement with thy ſeruauntes, for if thou do, there ſhall no fleſhe be ſaued in thy ſight. O Lord we confeſſe and ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>knowledge that it is our ſyns that hath cauſed thee to be moued vnto wrathe, &amp; to ſhewe ſuche tokens of thy diſpleaſure towardes vs in theſe our dayes, fyrfte with fire from heauen, whiche did beto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="tcp:16024:27"/>thy hotte burning indignation, and wrathfull diſpleaſure for ſynne whiche aboundeth at this day, &amp; then with ſuch horrible and monſtruous ſhapes againſt nature, as was neuer ſene in our daies, nor in no time before vs in this miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble countrey of oures: whiche all do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>token to vs none other thinge, but thye plagues to come vppon vs for our dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate and monſtrous lyfe and conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation: and our wonderfull and terry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deſtruction and deſolation (vnleſſe we ſpedely repent and turne to thee) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we haue ben ſo longe taught oute of thy moſt holy and ſacred worde, and yet no fruites of repentaunce or chriſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an life will appere.</p>
            <p>Woe and alas to theſe our daies, that neyther preachinge by worde moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, nor preaching by fyre moſt ter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rible, nor preaching by monſters moſte ougly &amp; horrible, wil flyrre vp our ſtony hartes, and awake vs from our ſinnes.</p>
            <p>We feare (oh Lorde) that the turkes with all the reſt of the vnbeleuing will condempne vs in the laſt day: whiche if they had ben ſo longe inſtructed by the comfortable preaching of thy word, and
<pb facs="tcp:16024:28"/>ſweete promiſes of thy goſpell, or ſeene the wonders whiche we haue ſeene, no doubt their righteouſenes woulde haue ſhined at this day, to our greate ſhame and confuſion. Thou haſt no leſſe war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vs (oh Lord) of thy feareful diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure &amp; heauie plagues at hande for our great wickednes, then thou dyddeſt the Iſraelites of that horryble deſtructyon which came vpon them: who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou firſt in mercy diddeſt call to repentaunce by the preachinge of thy worde, but when no warnynge wolde ſerue, thou diddeſt ſend them monſtrus and feareful ſignes and tokens, to declare that thy viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was not farre of. But they, like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs at this daye, dyd alwaies inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prete theſe thinges after the imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their owne vaine hartes, promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge to them ſelues peace when deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction was ouer their heades.</p>
            <p>Whiche thinges when we do call to minde (for as muche as they are writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for our learnynge, exaumple, and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge) it maketh vs to tremble &amp; quake for feare of thy iuſt iudgementes. For if thou haſt thus dealt with thine owne dears &amp; choſen chyldren, in token of thy
<pb facs="tcp:16024:28"/>great wrathe againſt ſynne, what ſhal we loke for? who do no leſſe deſerue thy feareful ſcourge (and of mercy it is that thou doeſte thus lenge forbeare vs) but liue as though there were no god at all to be reuenged vpon our ſinnes. It ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs to feare and cry inwardly in our ſowles: Come lord Ieſu,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apor.</hi> 22.</note> holy and trus in al thy doinges, and ſhorte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our dayes, brynge this our pilgremage to an ende, ſuffer vs not to heape ſynne vpon ſynne vnto the day of vengeaunce, leſte we be taught vp amongeſt the numbre of the wicked and reprobate, whiche ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſee thy louyng countenaunce.</p>
            <p>It maketh vs to crye to thee (o lorde) Let thy kingdome come &amp; ende this our ſynfull lyfe, wherin we do nothing but rouoke thee to wrath.<note place="margin">Pſal. 6.</note> Correcte vs not O lorde in thyne indignation, neyther chaſten vs in thine heauy diſpleaſure: &amp; thoughe to vs belongeth nothinge but ſhame and confuſion, though our offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces haue deſerued to be viſyted with the rodde, and our ſinnes with ſcourges:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.</note> yet in mercy lorde and with fatherly correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion chaſten vs, and thy louinge kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes take not away from vs.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:29"/>
            <p>To thee we flee for ſuccour, vnder the winges of thy mercy ſhall be our refuge vntill thou turne thy wrathfull counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce from vs.<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>57.</hi>
               </note> We knowe that thye mercy is aboue all thye workes, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as great as thy ſelfe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 2.</note> Therfore wil we ſay with holy Iob, though thou kill vs, yet wyll we put our truſt in thee.</p>
            <p>Thou cammeſt to comforte, and plucke out of the dungeo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hel, ſuch wretches as wee are:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 10.</note> thou art the good Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane that cameſte to heale our deadlye woundes: thou art that good phiſition that cameſt to cure our mortal infyrmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: thou arte the good ſhepeherd that cameſt to ſeke vs wanderinge and loſte ſheepe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 15.</note> and to bringe vs to thy folde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: and more then that thou art our brother,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.</note> fleſhe of our fleſh, and boane of our boanes; whiche haſte taſted of oure infirmities,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 53.</note> felte our temptations, and borne the burden of our ſynnes: Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore at thy handes wee looke for mercy againſte the daye of vengeaunce. And thoughe thou punyſhe vs, yet our hope is and euer ſhall be, that thy rodde ſhal no further touche vs then ſhall make to thy glory, our commoditie, &amp; the ſtreng
<pb facs="tcp:16024:29"/>thenyng and increace of our faythe.</p>
            <p>Let this thy preaching ſundry wayes (O lord) be ſufficient for our warning, and graunte that we maye ſpedely and from the bottome of our hartes repent, endeuour to do thy righteouſe and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed wyll reueled in thy word, and frame our lyues accordinge to the ſame: that we maye here liue in thye feare all the dayes of our lyfe, and after this our ſin ful courſe is ended, may dwel with-thee in thy bleſſed kyngedome, throughe the death and merites of Ieſus Chriſte our onely redemer. So be it.</p>
            <q>
               <p>When thy wrathe is kendeled (O Lorde) bleſſed are all they that put their truſt in thee.</p>
               <bibl>Pſal. 2.</bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>¶ A prayer for fayre weather.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> God and mercifull father, we acknowledge that we through our manifolde ſinnes haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued to be ſharpely rebuked and corrected of thee. But if thou ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt deale with vs after our ſynnes, we are not hable to abyde thy wrath &amp; heuy
<pb facs="tcp:16024:30"/>hand. Wherfore deale mercifully with vs (O Lorde) after the greatnes of thy goodnes, and the multitude of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, that we rather may reioyce and be thankeful vnto thee for the aboundance of thy great mercies, and louing kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, then be caſte downe and diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the heauy waight of thy hande.</p>
            <p>In thy handes (O lord) are both hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth: So gouerne them ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, we beſech thee for thy names ſake, that we maye haue ſeaſonable weather to receaue the fruites of the earth. Stay the immoderate plentie of rayne and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeaſonable weather, and powre rather vpon vs the plentyfull dewe of thy ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, that we may daily grow to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of chriſten menne. Take awaye from vs our ſtony hartes, &amp; geue vnto vs in the ſtede therof, hartes of fleſhe, that we may ceaſe at the length thus to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke thy wrathe to brynge vpon vs ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this ſo great a plague as the loſſe of the fruites of the earthe, eyther elles o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther plagues of thy iuſte iudgement.</p>
            <p>Graunte that we maye ſo repente vs of our former euils, that hereafter the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy fruites of true repentaunce may con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinually
<pb facs="tcp:16024:30"/>appere therin, and ſoo to paſſe ouer and to ende this our mortall lyfe, that at the laſt we may attaine vnto the bleſſed reſurrection and lyfe euerlaſting through Ieſus Chriſt our lorde. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>¶ A Prayer to be ſaid before the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauing of the communion.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Father of mercy and god of all conſolation, ſeinge all creatures doe knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and confeſſe thee to be theyr gouernoure and lorde,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 5.</note> it becommeth vs the workmanſhip of thine owne handes, at all times to reuerence and magnifie thy godly maieſtie: Fyrſte,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gent.</hi> 1.</note> for that thou haſt created vs to thine own ymage and ſimilitude, but chiefly becauſe thou haſt delyuered vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that euerlaſting deathe and dampnation,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. <hi>Gene.</hi> 3.</note> into the whiche Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than drewe mankinde by the meanes of ſynne: fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bondage wherof neyther man nor Angell was hable to make vs free,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 4. <hi>Hebre.</hi> 1. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 5.</note> but thou (o lorde) ryche in mercye and infinite in goodnes, haſte prouyded our redemption to ſtande in thine onely
<pb facs="tcp:16024:31"/>and welbeloued ſonne, whome of verye loue thou diddeſte geue to be made man lyke vnto vs in al thinges,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3. <hi>Hebre.</hi> 8. <hi>Hebre.</hi> 4. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>Eſ.</hi> 43.53. <hi>Mat</hi> 3.17 <hi>Iere.</hi> 31. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 6. <hi>Gene.</hi> 3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 3.</note> ſynne excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that in his body he mighte receyue the puniſhement of our tranſgreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by his death to make ſatiſfaction to thy iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and by his reſurrection to deſtroye him that was authour of deathe, and ſo to bringe againe lyfe to the worlde, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which the whole ofſpring of Adam was moſt iuſtely exiled.</p>
            <p>O lord we acknowledge that no cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was able to comprehende the le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth and breadth, the depenes and heighte of that thy moſt excellent loue whiche mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued thee to ſhew mercy where none was deſerued,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2. <hi>Io.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2. <hi>Gene.</hi> 6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. <hi>Eſai.</hi> 64. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.12 <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2 <hi>Luke.</hi> 11. <hi>Mar.</hi> 10. <hi>Math</hi> 26. <hi>Luke.</hi> 22. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> to promiſe and geue life, wher deathe had gotten victory: to receiue vs into thy grace whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we could do nothing but rebell againſt thy maieſtie. O lorde the blinde dulnes of our corrupt nature wyll not ſuffer vs ſufficiently to weigh theſe thy moſt ample benefites: yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe at the commaundemente of Ieſus Chriſt our lorde, we preſente our ſelues to this his table (whiche he hath lefte to be vſed in remembraunce of his deathe vntyll his comminge againe) to
<pb facs="tcp:16024:31"/>declare and witneſſe before the worlde, that by hym alone we haue receiued ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie and life:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Io.</hi> 8. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. <hi>Ro.</hi> 8. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. <hi>Ro.</hi> 3. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 14. <hi>Luke.</hi> 12. <hi>Luke.</hi> 22. <hi>Apo.</hi> 2. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2. <hi>Ephe</hi> 1. <hi>Apo.</hi> 13.</note> that by hym alone thou doeſt acknowledge vs to be thy chyldren and heires: that by hym alone we haue entrance to the throne of thy grace: that by him alone we are poſſeſſed in our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rituall kingdome, to eate and drinke at his table, with whom we haue our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation preſentely in heauen, and by whom our bodies ſhal be rayſed vppe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne from the duſt, and ſhal be placed with him in that endeles ioye, whiche thou (O father of mercie) haſt prepared for thine elect before the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>datio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the worlde was layed. And theſe moſt ineſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timable benefites we acknowledge and confeſſe to haue receiued of thy fre mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and grace,<note place="margin">Ro. <hi>3.</hi> Ephe. <hi>2.</hi> Tit. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> by thine only beloued ſon Ieſus Chriſte. For the whiche therfore we thy congregation, moued by thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpiryte,<note place="margin">Ro. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> render to thee all thanckes prayſe and glory for euer and euer.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>¶ A Thankeſgeuinge after the receauiuge of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munyon. *</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:32"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſte mercyfull Father, we render vnto thee all prayſe, thankes, honour and glory, for that it hath pleaſed thee of thy great mercies to grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto vs miſerable ſinners ſo ercellent a gift and treaſure, as to receaue vs into the felowſhip and company of thy deare ſonne Ieſus chriſt our lord,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.</note> whom thou haſt deliuered to death for vs, and haſte geuen him vnto vs as a neceſſary fode &amp; nouriſhment vnto euerlaſting life.<note place="margin">Rom. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note>
               <note place="margin">Io. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> And nowe wee beſech thee alſo (O heauenly father) to graunt vs this requeſt, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thou neuer ſuffer vs to become ſo vnkind, as to forget ſo worthy benefites, but rather imprint and faſten them ſure in our har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, that we may growe &amp; increaſe day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more and more in true faythe,<note place="margin">Luke. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> whych continually is exerciſed in all maner of good workes:<note place="margin">Gala. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> and ſo muche the rather, (O Lorde) confirme vs in theſe perilous dayes and rages of Sathan,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.</note> that wee maye conſtantly ſtande and continue in the confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſame, to the aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thy glory, which art God ouer all thinges bleſſed for euer.</p>
            <p>So be it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:32"/>
            <head>¶ A prayer to be ſayde before meate. **</head>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Eternall god,<note place="margin">Ebre. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> the very god of peace &amp; all conſolation, whych broughteſt againe from death our lorde Ieſus the great ſhep herde of the ſhepe throughe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloud of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euerlaſtinge couenante, make vs frute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in all good workes to do thy will, &amp; worke in vs that which is acceptable in thy ſighte: ſanctify vs throughout, and kepe our whole ſpyrite, ſoule, and bodye fautleſſe vnto the comming of thy deare ſonne our lord Ieſus Chriſt. Thou art faythfull O father who haſte promyſed this, who alſo ſhall bringe it to paſſe, to thee therfore be geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euerlaſting praiſe, honour, and glory.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>¶ A Thankeſgeuing after meate.</head>
            <p>MOſte bountifull &amp; gracious god, which feedeſt all fleſhe, and haſte promiſed that aſking of thee, we ſhall not lacke, if we firſt ſeke thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and the righteouſenes therof, we felinge preſently the benefite of this thy
<pb facs="tcp:16024:33"/>gracious promiſe in feeding our bodies with theſe corporall benefites, do render vnto the moſt harty thaks for the ſame, beſechi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the likewiſe to fede our ſoules with that heuenly fode which periſheth not,<note place="margin">Ihon. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> but abideth into euerlaſting life: ſo that we being noryſhed by thy goodnes both in body and ſoule, may be apte and redy to doe all good workes which thou haſt prepared for vs to walk in, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde.</p>
            <p>Vnto hym that loued vs &amp; waſſhed vs from our ſinnes in his bloud and made vs kinges &amp; prieſtes vnto God his father,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.</note> be all glory, power, and dominion for euermore. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>¶ A prayer for true mortification.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> God my creatour, preſeruer, &amp; euerlaſtinge defendour, where fyrſt in my creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I was made lyke vnto thyne owne likeneſſe: the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll (alas) hath ſynce by Adams faule, made me oughlye, monſtruous, and lyke euyll fauoured to hym ſelfe. For what
<pb facs="tcp:16024:33"/>are now lord mine earthly me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres,<note place="margin">Colo. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> but as is written in the .iii. to the Colloſſ. adulterie, whoredome, vncleannes, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural luſtes, euyl co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cupiſcence, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes (which is the worſhippynge of Idoles) and ſuche other, for the whiche thy wrath is wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to come vpon the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of vnbelefe. Neuertheleſſe (lorde) of thy gret mercie and goodnes againſt this very great miſchiefe, a much grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter remedy thy fatherly prouidence hath ordeined.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Io.</hi> 3.</note> For thou haſt ſent Ieſus chriſt thy deere and onely naturall ſonne into this worlde, the vale of miſeries, to loſe the workes of the deuyll, and to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way my ſinnes. Therfore Sathan hath now nothing to bragge of, for through Chriſt all that beleue in thee and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come thy children,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ihon.</hi> 5.</note> do ouercome y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world the fleſhe and the deuyl.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ihon.</hi> 5.</note> And this is the victorie whiche ouercommeth them all, euen our Fayth.<note place="margin">Io. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> That Faith I meane which is perſwaden that who ſo euer be leueth in chriſt ſhal not periſhe but haue euerlaſting life.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5.</note> That fayth whiche be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loueth the teſtimonie to be true whiche thou (God the Father) doeſte teſtifie of thy ſonne, ſo making thee no lyer, and
<pb facs="tcp:16024:34"/>this is that teſtimonie, that thou haſte geuen vs eternall life.<note place="margin">Ro. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> That faith whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che beleueth that thou father, who ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedſt vp Chriſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death ſhalt alſo quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken our mortall bodies through thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirite dwellig in vs.<note place="margin">Io. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> That faith whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che beleueth it to be true which thy ſon Chriſte affirmed, with a double othe, ſaying: Verely, verely, I ſay vnto you, he that beleueth in mee the workes that I do, the ſame ſhall he do, and greatter workes then theſe ſhall he do, becauſe I go vnto my father.<note place="margin">Iohn. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> And fynally y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fayth whiche beleueth, that now Chriſt hath ben lifte vppe on the croſſe, he ſhal draw all thinges vnto hym: this fayth (I ſay) is the victory whicke ouercommeth our ennemies, the deuyll, the worlde, and our fleſhe.<note place="margin">Iohn. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> Thou therfore (lorde father) whiche haſt promiſed to geue what ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer I ſhall aſke in thy deere Sonne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus name, for thy great mercy and infal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lible truethes ſake, do nowe in mee the thynge that he came for: loſe in me the workes of the deuyl,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iho.</hi> 3.</note> and take away my ſynnes I beſeche thee, make ſtedfaſt my Faithe confidence in thy promiſed mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies &amp; merciful promiſes:<note place="margin">Iohn. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> ſo that I aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly
<pb facs="tcp:16024:34"/>beleui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in thee may haue (as thou promiſeſt) euerlaſting lyfe, &amp; makynge thee (deere God) no lyar, maye beleue, feele, and knowe in my hart and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the ſame euerlaſtyng lyfe is thy mere &amp; free gift vnto me, yea already of thy great goodneſſe, vndoubtedly geuen mee, beinge now tranſlated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death to life. Of a thanckefulnes wherof Lorde cauſe me now dayly to mortifie my erth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly membres.<note place="margin">Ro. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> Yea (dere father) ſithe thy ſpirite which raiſed vp Chriſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death, dwelleth within mee, do thou (who rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedſt Chriſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death) quicke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my mortal body through thy ſpirite ſo dwellyng in me, I beſeche thee.<note place="margin">Iohn. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> Yea lorde Ieſu ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy promiſe (becauſe thou art now gone to thy father) make me work this wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derful great worke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thou ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt of: I meane, make me,<note place="margin">Collo. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> being of my ſelf but a lumpe of ſynne and a monſter moſte ougly (as the vyces whereon the membres of my earthly body aboue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be compacte doo proue) make me (I ſaye) yet throughe thy grace, to hate, abhorre, flee and ſubdue all adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, whoredome, vncleannes, vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rall luſtes, euyl concupiſcence, vnordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
<pb facs="tcp:16024:35"/>deſyres, wantonnes, tendernes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licatenes, idlenes, drunkennes, glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony, ſlouthfulnes, diſtruſte, diſpaire, ignoraunce, weakenes, wilfulnes, Ido<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>latry, ſuperſtition, hypocriſie, hereſye, errour, ſectes, variaunce, ſtrife, wrath, enuie, ſlaunders, lyeng, ſwearing, cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng, vayne glory, pride, couetouſenes, thefte, diſceite, flattery, and what ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer elles (lord) feighteth or rebelleth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy holy ſpirite. And then (lorde Father) I will boaſt and make vaunte agaynſte myne ennemie the deuyll, that I haue doone greater workes then thy dere ſonne Ieſus dyd, at what tyme he ſpake theſe wordes amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the iewes, becauſe,<note place="margin">Iohn. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> albeit he vanquiſſehed Sathan, yet in as muche as he hym ſelfe was vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly without ſynne, the victorie ſemed the wore eaſy: But I to vanquiſhe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, being my ſelfe altogether ſynful, yea contrary to my moſt ſynfull nature to ſubdue ſynne, the deuyll, and myne owne fleſhe, it ſeemeth a more victorye and greater worke then the other. For the whiche neuertheleſſe, I wyll with all ſubmiſſion acknowledge vnto thy di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyne maieſtie taht y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole victory lord
<pb facs="tcp:16024:35"/>in deede is thine, and thy holy ſpirit the begynner and fyniſher bothe of the will and worke. Nowe therfore, Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu, ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>then me with thy grace &amp; myght, that thou mayſte by me a moſte ſynfull wretch, drawe al theſe my earthly mem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bres and horrible vices before reherſed, vnder my feete, that I maye not onely mightely fyght againſte them, but alſo ſubdue them, ſo that they may al turne to the beſt for me,<note place="margin">Rom. <hi>8.</hi> Io. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> as mete matter wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I may exerciſe my fayth powre forth harty prayer, and geue thee moſt hartye thanckes for victorie: whereby I maye learne &amp; haue experience that thou haſte in me drawen althinges vnto thee in ſo muche as thou thus (lord) of thy diuine power, draweſt bothe the deuill and the ſynne that dwelleth in mee, to ſet forth thy honour and glory. whiche thyng for thy mercies ſake brynge to paſſe, O God my crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toure, preſeruer, and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinge de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dour.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:36"/>
            <head>¶ A Prayer of a chriſtian man, expreſſing his great anguiſhe &amp; heuines of minde that he had before time for his ſinnes, &amp; for that he felt not his hart co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted in the ioy of gods great loue towardes him, with the maner of his prayers &amp; groninges which he then made, &amp; nowe pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth forth againe vnto god for his grace &amp; aſſiſtance in his new aſſaultes. wherby the broken harted &amp; afflicted for their ſinnes maye learne to ſtirre vp &amp; ſtrengthen their faith and hope in like dangers and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of conſcience.</head>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ven in the myddes of the deſperate aſſaultes of my ſoule, the intollerable he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uineſſe of my minde hath heretofore (Lorde) cryed as ſhrill in thine eares as thoughe I had ſhryked and with lamen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tations cryed out, ſaying: Help, helpe me my god, my creatour, my moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident keper, and euerlaſting defender, for beholde I peryſhe.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> On this occaſion (Lorde) that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines of mynd did heretofore aſſault me I remembred that thou haddeſte manye tymes ſet before myne eyes the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full greatues of thy moſt tender loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes
<pb facs="tcp:16024:36"/>me by great multitude of thy be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nefites powred vpon me, whiche bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fytes euery of thy workes (as they came before mine eyes) gaue me iuſte occaſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be mindefull of.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> Wolde not (thought I) if I had in a maner any grace at all, wolde not ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the loue brynge nowe into my harte a wonderfull delectation, comforte &amp; ioye in god for the ſame?</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4</hi> And againe, coulde ſuche delyghte in goddes ſwete mercy and tender loue towardes me (if I were not as euyll as a caſt awaye that were none of goddes chyldren) be without lothing of my ſyn, and luſt &amp; deſire to do goddes holy wyl? And theſe thinges thought I (fye vpon the vnthankeful wretche) are either not at all in me, or elles in deede ſo coldelye and ſclenderly that they beynge truelye waied and compared to righteouſenes,<note place="margin">Eſa. <hi>64.</hi>
               </note> are more vile then a ſylthye clothe ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in corrupte bloudde.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5</hi> Oh (thought I) I am aferd I haue deceyued my ſelfe: for thy ſeruauntes at al times (I trowe) feele otherwiſe then I nowe do, the fruites of thy ſpirite: as Loue, Ioye, Peace and ſuche lyke.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:37"/>
            <p>But my loue (alas) towards thee, what is it? my ioye (oh woe is my hart there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) is not once almoſt felte of me, for my very ſoule within me (as Dauid in his heuynes ſaid) refuſeth comfort, and fareth as though it dyd vtterly deſpaire.<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>77.</hi>
               </note> And what peace can I feele then, or cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie of thy fauoure and loue? Iuſtely may I powre out this dolorous lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Sion: the lorde hath forſaken me,<note place="margin">Eſai. <hi>49.</hi>
               </note> and my lorde hath forgotten mee:</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6</hi> Euen in the middes (I ſay) of theſe my former deſperate aſſaultes, myne in tollerable heuines cryed to my god, and from heauen he heard my gronynges, &amp; therupon firſt prepared my hert to aſke comfort of him, &amp; then he heard my prai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er and gaue me ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tefully my aſking.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7</hi> Oh my ſoule, conſider wel that thou art neuer hable to declare the excedynge goodnes of god in this that he heard the very deſires of thee being afflicted. who is ſoo redy fauourablye to graunte the requeſtes of the afflicted, that often ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes he taryeth not vntyll they do call, but or euer they cal vpon him, he fauou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rably heareth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: as the pſalmiſt ſaith, the deſires of the afflicted thou heareſte
<pb facs="tcp:16024:37"/>(O lorde) thou prepareſt theyr hartes &amp; thine care heareth fauourably.<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8</hi> Oh lorde my god, marueilous thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are theſe, whether I conſyder this marueilous maner of thy hearing, orels the marueilous nature and propertye of thy goodnes. Marueilous (no doubt) is that thy hearinge, wherby the very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of the afflicted are hearde, but mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che more marueilous is this thye good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which taryeth not vntyl the afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted do deſire thy help, but prepareth firſt their hartes to deſyre, and then thou ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt them their deſires.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>9</hi> Yea Lorde (worthye of all praiſe) it can not otherwiſe be. For how ſhouldſt thou do otherwiſe then thy nature and propertie is? art not thou very goodnes and mercy it ſelf? how canſt thou then, but pitie and helpe miſerie?</p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>10</hi> Art not thou both the creatour and alſo the conſeruer of all thinges? In ſo much as the lyons whelpes roaryng af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their pray do ſeeke their foode at thy handes,<note place="margin">Pſa. <hi>104.</hi> Pſal. <hi>147.</hi>
               </note> and the rauens byrdes lackyng meate do call vpon thee.</p>
            <p n="11">
               <hi>11</hi> If then thy fatherly prouidence and tender care (O lorde) vpon all thy crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb facs="tcp:16024:38"/>be ſo great, that the very beaſtes &amp; foules haue this experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in their neceſſities, that their rorin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and criynges haue the ſtrengthe of earneſt callinges and beſechinges: how muche rather do theſe ſyghinges, gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges, and deſperate heuines of men, but chiefely of all thoſe whiche beleue in thee, crye &amp; call loude in thine eares, though they ſpeake neuer a word at all?</p>
            <p n="12">
               <hi>12</hi> Shulde I then nowe diſpeire of thy fatherly mercy, whiles preſently I feele thee ſtirre vp my ſoule &amp; harte to craue helpe at thy hande?<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>77.</hi>
               </note> ſhulde I thinke that thou wilt abſent thy ſelfe for euer? that thou wylte be noo more intreated? that thy mercy is cleane gone, and thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe come vtterly to an ende, and that thou wilt now ſhut vp thy louing kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in diſpleaſure?</p>
            <p n="13">
               <hi>13</hi> Nay god forbydde: for all alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are of thy right hande and turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to the beſt, to them that feare thee. All this is no more but myne owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie,<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>77.</hi>
               </note> for god is euer one, his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes be vnfallible, and his loue towardes his euerlaſtingly duringe.</p>
            <p n="14">
               <hi>14</hi> I wyll therfore in this my preſent
<pb facs="tcp:16024:38"/>temptation and greuous aſſault, powre out my heuines of hart before thee (dere father) yea I will with gronynges lifte vp my ſoule vnto thee, from whence I aſſuredly knowe my helpe is comming. I will alſo for my preſent comforte,<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>77.</hi>
               </note> cal to remembraunce (O lorde my god) thy tender mercies towardes me alredy ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed, the multitude of thy benefites, the greatnes of the ſame, the longe conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuaunce of theim, euen from my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception vntyll this inſtante, and fynally thy continuall luſt and deſyre to powre them vpon me.</p>
            <p n="15">
               <hi>15.</hi> And moreouer ſith thy goodnes is ſo great (O lord) that thou doeſt not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pitty miſery, but alſo calleſt the heuy harted and afflicted vnto the, promiſing that thou wilt eaſe their miſery: and for as muche as,<note place="margin">Mat. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> by the motion of thy good ſpirite I loth &amp; abhorre my ſines, I felt the greuouſenes of them, and thy heauy wrath towardes me for the ſame, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally what nede I haue of thy gracious aide and ſuccoure: therfore (Lord father) in thy ſonne Chriſtes name, wyth ſure confidence and truſte in thine infallible promiſe, in this mine anguiſh and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:16024:39"/>I come vnto thee at thy mercyfull calling, and craue comfort at thy hand. For this I know wel, that when I loth my ſinnes, thou doeſt vtterly forget the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I fele the greuous burden of them, thy mercy ſwalloweth them vp, when I fele what I wante, thou wylt aſſuredly graunt it me. For ſith thou moueſt my harte to deſire helpe, how ſhould I miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt but thou wilt for thy truthes ſake, geue me mine aſkinge?</p>
            <p n="16">
               <hi>16.</hi> Yea, where I knowe not howe or what to deſire as I ought, thy holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite graciouſly workinge in me, maketh interceſſion mightely for me,<note place="margin">Rom. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> with gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings which can not be expreſſed, &amp; ther withal certifieth my ſpirite that by adop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, through thy great mercy and good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, I am become thy childe and heire.</p>
            <p n="17">
               <hi>17.</hi> Why ſhould I not then be of good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort &amp; ioyfull in thee my God? For if thou be on my ſide, who can be againſte me?<note place="margin">Rom. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> who diddeſte not ſpare thine owne ſonne, but gaueſt him for me, euen whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I was thine enemy, how ſhalt thou not with him nowe that by his deathe I am broughte into thy fauoure, geue me all thinges with him and for his ſake? who
<pb facs="tcp:16024:39"/>ſhal lay any thing to the charge of thine elects? it is thou lord that iuſtifieſt me, who then ſhall condempne me? It is Chriſte that hath died for me, yea rather that is riſen againe for me, who alſo is ſet on thy right hande, and hathe taken poſſeſſion, yea and perpetually maketh there interceſſion for me, vntil that ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full day be come when I ſhall haue full fruition of the moſt glorious preſence of thy diuyne maieſtie in that kingedome whych thou haſt prepared before the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world,<note place="margin">Ephe. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> but in time (to thy gracious goodnes thoughte beſte) made knowen to me by geuinge thy holy ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite into my hart, wherby when I fyrſte Lorde beleued thy holy worde (whych is thine own power to ſaue al that beleue) I was ſealed,<note place="margin">Rom. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> confyrmed and ſtablyſhed in certaynty of that thyne euerlaſtynge kingdome and inheritaunce.</p>
            <p>For the which ineſtimable benefite of thy rich grace (Oh Lorde my God) I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche thee (euen for the loue thou bareſt to Chriſt Ieſu thy ſonne, and the mercy thou haddeſte on him when he cryed on the Croſſe,<note place="margin">Mat. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> my God my God why haſte thou forſaken me) helpe, help I ſay, and
<pb facs="tcp:16024:40"/>inflame my hart with loue ſo plenteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly towardes thee againe, that I may be eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſwallowed vp in the ioyful feling of the ſame, in ſuch ſort that I may of very thankfulneſſe loue thee my God alone, thee I ſay my deare God, and nothinge but thee and for thy ſake. Oh holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite whoſe worke this is in me, increaſe this thy worke, of thyne infinite mercy, &amp; preſerue me that I neuer become vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull vnto thee therefore. Amen, deare god. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>¶ Remedies againſt ſynfull motions and voluptuous te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptations.</head>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> 
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt remember that ſinne is ſo heynous a thing that god by his iuſtice might worthe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly dampne the for the ſame, and is therfore to be abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as a ſwete poiſon; a flattering death &amp; deſtruction of thy ſowle, which wold cutte thee of from god thy fauiour, and make thee bonde ſlaue to Sathan thye deadly enemie.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> Auoyde therfore euen at the firſt, the occaſions thereof, and betymes quaſhe
<pb facs="tcp:16024:40"/>out the braines of the children of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon againſt the hard ſtones,<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>137.</hi>
               </note> whiles they be yet younge &amp; weake, leaſt when they be growne elder &amp; ſtronger, they daſhe thee to peeces.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> And for remedy againſt the ſame, flee vnto god, who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth thee to call vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym in thy troubles, and promiſeth to delyuer thee, and will not ſuffer thee to be further tempted then he wil make awaye out wherby thou ſhalte eſcape:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.</note> &amp; doubte not but he that cauſeth thee to hate the ſynne whiche thy nature is to loue, wyl deliuer thee alſo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the daun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger therof, and make thee to triumphe ouer Sathan, to his confuſion, to gods glory, and to thy great comforte. which are the cauſes that our tender louynge father ſendeth te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptations vnto vs &amp; and he that is not tempted, what is he?<note place="margin">1. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 1</note>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4</hi> Nowe after thou haſt obteyned the victory; remembre two thinges, firſt to geue moſt harty thanckes to god for his grace and aſſiſtance, wherby thou haſte ouercome, and he not vnthanckefull in any wyſe: and then, that he who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually goeth about lyke a roaryng ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſeekyng whom he may deuoure, will
<pb facs="tcp:16024:41"/>not be long or farre away from the, but wyll attempte agayne the ſame or as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll wayes to ouercome thee.</p>
            <p>Watche therfore and praye.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>¶ A prayer for preſente helpe in temptation.**</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eare father, to whome it is more eaſie to do all thinges then for me to thyncke anye one good thing, Lo do thou but ſpeake a worde and thy deadly ſicke ſeruaunte my ſoule ſhall be made whole. Helpe (O Lord) &amp; let thy ſtrength ſuffiſe againſt my weakeneſſe, and thy holy ſpirite againſte my ſynfull fleſhe and olde man. Thou art true and faithfull (O Father) who haſt promyſed that I ſhall not bee tempted further then thou wile make me able to beare.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.</note> Geue therefore thy power vnto thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt, that I may with a ſtronge fayth in thyne infallible truthe and promyſed mercy, vanquiſhe &amp; ſubdue what ſo ouer rebelleth againſt thy moſt bleſſed wills Do this O Father, for thy ſonne Ieſus Chriſtes ſake our deare Lorde and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious redemer. Amen</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:41"/>
            <head>¶ A Prayer to God the Father for the true knowledge of the myſtery of our rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption in Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>
               </hi> Almyghty God and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our lorde Ieſus Chriſt, and by hym alſo our father, the father of all mercy and god of all conſolation, haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye vppon vs and heare our prayers. We moſt humbly beſeche thee for thy deere ſonne Ieſus Chryſtes ſake, his merites and cruel death, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che he ſuffered to delyuer vs from eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall deathe and the power of darkenes, geue into our harts the ſpirite of truth, to worke in vs a true, liuely, and ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſte faithe, that the cleare lyghte and brighteneſſe of thy goſpell the glorye of Chriſt, may ſhyne vnto vs and lyghten our myndes, that we may learne &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande the wonderfull and vnſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able rycheſſe of the miſteric of our rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion in Chriſt and by Chryſt. O father of glory geue vnto vs the ſpirite of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome, &amp; brynge vs vnto the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of this thy beloued ſonne Ieſus
<pb facs="tcp:16024:42"/>Chriſte and the knowledge of thy ſelfe. Open and lyghten the eyes of our min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and vnderſtandinge,<note place="margin">Ephe. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> that we maye knowe what the hope is wherunto thou haſt called vs, and howe ryche the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of thine inheritaunce is vppon thy ſainctes, and the excedinge greatnes of thy power towardes vs: that by trewe fayth, vnderſtanding and knowledge of thine eternall wiſedome (whiche is Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte) we may be in deede as wee are called, true chriſtians and vnfained profeſſours of thye holy name, to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe thee in ſpirite and truthe, and to ſette forthe the glory of thy grace geuen vnto vs in Chriſt Ieſus our lord. Amen</p>
            <p>O dere father write in our hartes loue to thy lawe, hate to all ſynne, thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of heart and continual heate of thy holy ſpirite for thy ſonne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſtes ſake. To whom with thee and thy holy ſpirite be all honour, maieſtie, glory, thankes, rule, empire, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion for euer more.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:42"/>
            <head>¶ A prayer to be vſed of all ſortes of men and at all times.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>
               </hi> Lord God for thy great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies ſake, grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto me theſe my petycions whych I ſhall make vnto the in Ieſus Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes name, and endue me with thy grace that I maye aſke of thee in ſuch ſorte as thou requireſt, to the honour, glory, and prayſe of thy holy name, to the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce of thy worde, the profitte of thy people, and to my conſolation and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte, throughe Ieſus Chriſte our onely ſauiour and readeuter. So be it.</p>
            <p>O Lord thou great and terryble god, thou that kepeſt couenant &amp; merry with theym that loue thee and doe thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes, let thyne eares be open that thou mayſt heare the praiers of thy ſeruaunte, which I make before thee at this time, haue mercy vpon me thy pore creature, &amp; worke of thine handes, for I haue ſinned, &amp; done wickedly, and haue offended thy maieſty greuouſly, in that I haue gone backe, &amp; departed from all thy preceptes and iudgementes, &amp; haue not folowed thy ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes the prophets
<pb facs="tcp:16024:43"/>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpake vnto me in thy name, but haue from day to day prouoked thy iuſt wrath and indignation agaynſt me.</p>
            <p>O Lorde I knowledge and confeſſe my manifolde ſinnes and wyckedneſſe, the whiche I haue vnrighteouſely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt thee in thought, worde, &amp; dede, fro my youth vp vntill this day, for the which I am hartely ſory, and do vnfainedly repent, purpoſing euermore through the aſſiſtaunce of thy grace, to walke in a newe life.</p>
            <p>Remember not lord the numbre of my miſdedes I beſech the, but accordinge to thy great mercyes thinke vpon me.</p>
            <p>Call to remembraunce for Chriſtes ſake thy louing kindnes and thy tender mercy, the which hath euer bene of olde.</p>
            <p>Hyde not thou thy face from me, nor caſt not of thy ſeruaunte in thy diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, for I confeſſe my ſinnes vnto thee, and hide not mine vnrighteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>For thy mercies ſake deliuer me from al my ſinnes, and make me not a ſcorne vnto the folyſhe.</p>
            <p>Tourne not away thy mercy fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, but let thy moſt louing kindnes &amp; truth alwaies preſerue me.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:43"/>
            <p>Helpe me for thy names ſake, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer me in thy ſtrength.</p>
            <p>Heare my prayer (O lord) and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the wordes of my mouth, for my miſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dedes preuayle agaynſt me. O be thou mercifull vnto my ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Let the ſorowfull ſighyng of thy pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner come before thee, and according to the power of thyne arme preſerue thoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> be appoynted to dye for thy iuſt cauſe.</p>
            <p>O Lord comforte the ſoule of thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, for vnto thee do I flee for ſuccour.</p>
            <p>Teache me to number my dayes that I may apply my hart vnto wiſdome.</p>
            <p>Satiſfie me with thy mercy, and that ſone, ſo ſhall I reioyce and be gladde in thee all the dayes of my lyfe.</p>
            <p>Looke not extremely what is done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſe in me, for I haue ſinned againſte heauen and before thee, and am no more worthy to be called thy ſonne: yet lorde of thy great goodnes, powre down ſome of the cromes that fall fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy childrens table and make me as one of the leaſt of them.</p>
            <p>Rewarde me not accordyng to my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruings, for then I muſt nedes periſhe: for vnto me perteyneth nothinge but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
<pb facs="tcp:16024:44"/>ſhame, confuſion, and damnation: but with thee ther is mercy, forgeuenes, and ſaluacion.</p>
            <p>O Lorde therefore doe I come vnto thee, not hopyng in myne owne righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, but truſting onely in thy greate mercies and promiſes made vnto me in Chryſt Ieſu my lorde, for whoſe ſake, I beſeth thee to clenſe me from al my ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and do away all mine iniquities.</p>
            <p>For thy tender mercy ſake, lay not my ſinnes to my charge, but forgeue that is paſte and geue me grace to amende my lyfe, to declyne from ſinne, and incline to vertue, that I may walke in a perfect harte, a cleue comience, and ſingle eye before thee this daye or nyght and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
            <p>Remember not forde myne offences, nor the offences of my forefathers, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther take thou beingeance of my ſinnes, ſpare me good Lorde, ſpare me, whome thou haſt redemed with thy moſt precy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous blonde, and be not angrye with me for euer: ſpare me good lord, ſpare me.</p>
            <p>Put me not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy preſence (oh thou god of al comfort) but incline thine eare vnto my callyng.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:44"/>
            <p>Strengthen thy Seruaunte with the power of thy right hande, and helpe the Sonne of thy handmayden.</p>
            <p>Replenyſhe my hart with grace wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p>Comforte my ſoule with thy ſwete promyſes, and let thy mercies couer my infirmities.</p>
            <p>For the deathe and bloudſhedynge of thy Chriſt (O Lord) conſider myne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, which are many, and helpe to heale myne imperfection, &amp; delyuer me from al kyndes of euilles, that I do not obey vnto them: as from adultery, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, vncleanneſſe, wantonnes, ydo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>latry, good lord deliuer mee. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> witch craft, lyeng, hatred, varyaunce, zeale, wrath, ſtrife, ſedition, good lorde dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer mee. From ſectes, enuiyng, whyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering, backebityng, bringing vp of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll tumours, good lorde delyuer mee. From murther, drunkennes, gluttony, and from the ſpirite of euyl teloſie, good lorde deliuer me. From enuiynge of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which loue thee &amp; thy people more then I, or be beloued of thee or of thye people more than I am: from ſwelling at other mennes giftes, good lorde deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:16024:45"/>mee. From ſurmiſynge, murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe, lowring, grudging, mutteringe when wordes be not ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to my mind, good lorde for thy great mercies ſake de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liuer mee, and geue me grace that I do at no tyme enuye any good man or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunes loue, but labour to increaſe it, that their proſperſtie in worde &amp; prayſe of other may be my conſolation and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyſynge.</p>
            <p>O lord graunt me that I may be low in myne owne ſyght, to ſubmit my ſelf to beare all occaſions, to wreſtle wyth fleſhe and bloudde and get the victory.</p>
            <p>Graunt me this gyfte that I maye be ſwyft to heare, ſlowe to ſpeake, &amp; ſlowe to wrathe, that my hart do not go after any euyll and wicked imaginations.</p>
            <p>Geue me grace to walke ſoo that I geue none euill occaſions, and to auoid all ſuſpitious thinges wherby euyll oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions maye growe.</p>
            <p>O Lorde aſſiſt mee with thye ſpirite, that I may labour to mainteyne peace, to increaſe loue, and to further vertue.</p>
            <p>Graunte (O mercifull father) that I may proſper in all vertue, in long ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, gentlenes, goodnes, faithfulnes,
<pb facs="tcp:16024:45"/>mekenes, temperaunce, ſtrength, and pacience, with all ſuche like vertues as are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded in thy holy law for mee to walke in.</p>
            <p>O lorde geue me ioye in thy holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, that I may reioyce in thy holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures, that al my whole pleaſure, fely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, and conſolation, may be in thy ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly woorde night and daye, in readinge, thinking, &amp; talkinge of the ſame, to thy glory and my edifienge.</p>
            <p>Aſſiſt thy ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t againſt this world with the vaine pompe, pleaſure &amp; beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thereof, that it maye be vnto me as vile duſt, ſlime, fylthynes, and aſſhes, that I maye vſe it as thoughe I vſed it not, and that it may ſerue me, and I not it, that I may take my part therof vnto my neceſſitie, with thankeſgeuing, that I do not vſe thy creatures voluptuouſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but that I may at al tymes liue righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſly, ſoberly, and godly in this lyfe.</p>
            <p>Geue me grace to walke with a good conſcience bothe before thee and towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des all men, in bying and ſellinge, and in all other my doinges, to caſt away al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyinge, craft, and diſceite, that I be not a reader of thy holy worde, and a talker
<pb facs="tcp:16024:46"/>onely, but that it may appere alſo in my lyfe and conuerſation.</p>
            <p>O Lorde graunte vnto thy ſeruaunte the ſtrengthe of thy holy ſpirite, to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due this bodye of ſynne with the whele luſtes therof, that it may be made obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient both in wyll, minde, &amp; membres, to do thy will, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it may be weake, vile, ſimple, and of no reputation in it ſelfe by the way of faſtinge, prayer, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of thy lawe, that I may be low harted, humble minded, gentle ſpry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and to all vertues obedient.</p>
            <p>Geue me grace O lorde to brydle my mouth from al vayne and lyght commu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nication, and geue me an vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding hearte with ſuche diſcretyon, that ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fylthynes nor foliſhe talkinge, nor ieſtinge whiche are not comely, procede out of my mouthe, but rather geuing of thankes.</p>
            <p>O Lord my ſauiour, increaſe my faith in thee, and in thy Chriſte, and make it ſtronge to beleue thy promyſes.</p>
            <p>O Lorde my redemer, increaſe in me a loue to do thy wyll, and to thy ryghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous people.</p>
            <p>O Lorde my iuſtifyer, increaſe in me
<pb facs="tcp:16024:46"/>a ſure hope of my ſaluation withoute doubt or wauering in aduerſitie, &amp; with out pride or preſumption in proſperytie: ſo that in aduerſitie I maye be pacient, and geue thankes in proſperitie, &amp; ſerue thee with reuerence and godly feare all the dayes of my lyfe.</p>
            <p>Increaſe in me Lord al other vertues agreable to a godly lyfe, for I come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee my god as vnto the wel &amp; euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting fountaine of health and ſaluation.</p>
            <p>O heauenly father, graunt vnto mee &amp; al other, whereſoeuer they be diſperſed throughout the whole world, which pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſe thy holy worde, ſo to lyue that we may dye to ſinne, and leade a godly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> walking innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly before thee.</p>
            <p>Preſerue and defende thy ſeruaunte from all falſe opinions, that I be not deceyued and caryed awaye in errour of the wicked, but that I maye growe in grace and knoweledge of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>O Lord geue me a reuerent and pure vnderſtanding of thy holy word, that I may therby auoyde al raſhe iudgemente and peruerſe interpretations.</p>
            <p>O Lorde geue me wiſedome knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="tcp:16024:47"/>and vnderſtandinge to perceyue thoſe falſe, lying, &amp; flatteryng ſpirytes, whiche doe deceyue the hartes of inne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centes and begyle vnſtable ſoules.</p>
            <p>O Lorde make me to be content with thys woman which thou haſt geuen me to be my wyfe that we maye godly lyue together accordynge to thy holy ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce.</p>
            <p>Geue her an hearte of vnderſtanding, and ſet thy feare alway before her eyes, that ſhe may be obedient in word, dede, and thought to all that is thy wil.</p>
            <p>O Lord geue vs the power of thy holy Spirite, to rule, gouerne, and bryng vp theſe our children and familie, in al god lye feare and knoweledge of thy holye worde, and that we maye be vnto them an example in all godlynes and vertue, to the prayſe of thy holy name.</p>
            <p>Saue my ſoule (oh my God) whether it be throughe proſperitie or aduerſitie, loſſe or gayne, ſickenes or health, life or deathe.</p>
            <p>Ayde, ſtrengthen, ſuccour, and defend thy ſeruaunt, in all aduerſitye, tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and temptacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſuffer not him to be tempted aboue his ſtrength.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:47"/>
            <p>Increaſe my ioye, that I may reioyce in perſecution, &amp; embrace it to my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſola<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion &amp; comfort, &amp; thinke my felfe happie and bleſſed, when I am counted worthy to ſuffer rebuke for thy names ſake.</p>
            <p>Take from my hearte the care of all worldly thinges, only ſet before my eies the ioye of the croſſe of Chriſte, that I maye take comforte therin, and deſpyſe the ſhame, for the great rewarde that is laide vppe in heauen for all thoſe that with pacience ſuffer in aduerſitie, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in well doinge vnto the ende.</p>
            <p>O Lorde neither lay thou preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnto thy ſeruauntes charge, nor loke not vppon my vilenes, whiche am but duſt, earth, and aſhes: yet lorde I haue taken vpon me &amp; am bolde to come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, throughe the merites of Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes death and bloud ſhedyng, to lay my prayers before thee, requiringe merry, pardon, and forgeueneſſe of all my ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and alſo the aſſiſtance of thy grace, to do thy wyll all the dayes of my lyfe, and to obteyne all theſe my peticions, through Ieſus Chriſt thy dere ſonne, &amp; my onely ſauiour: To whom be all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glory nowe and euer.</p>
            <closer>Amen. <signed>Iohn Lydley.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:48"/>
            <head>¶ A Godly Prayer for all Chriſten men.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>
               </hi> Almighty &amp; euer liuynge god, thou God of all power, before whoſe eyes all thinges lye na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and bare, haue regarde vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to me, moſte miſerable ſynner, &amp; ſhews me the light of thy mercies, let my prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers aſcende vp before thy preſence, and be accepted in thy ſight, for Ieſus Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ſake. Geue thy holy ſpirite into my heart (Oh Lord) and lighten my vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that I maye dwell in the feare of thy name al the dayes of my life, that I maye knowe thee, the onely true god and Ieſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſente. For I come vnto thee (Oh Lorde thou louer of our ſoules) not hoping in mine owne righteouſenes, but truſting onely vpon the multitude of thy great mercies whiche thou haſt layde forthe before the eyes of all people, offering ſaluation to the whole worlde, and haſte promyſed that who ſo euer he be of the whole ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of man, that wyll obey to thy grace, Repent, and tourne vnfaynedly from his ſynnes, he ſhall haue free re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion
<pb facs="tcp:16024:48"/>and forgeuenes through Ieſus Chriſt our lord, whiche is our onely ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocate and mediatour, in whom our ſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uation lyeth, of whom thou haſt ſayde: This is my deere ſonne, in whom I am well pleaſed, &amp; well pacifyed. For this thy ſonnes ſake (by whom I am bold to come vnto thee, whiche appereth nowe inthy ſyght, making continuall inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for vs) Haue mercy vpon me (O thou mightye God) and forgeue mee all my ſynnes, which I haue vnrighteouſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly committed againſt thee, in thoughte, worde &amp; dede. Oh let me feele thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies towardes mee, for I do confeſſe my ſynnes vnto thee (Oh lord) and hide not mine vnrighteouſenes, I doo acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge mine offences, and accuſe my ſelfe before thee of all my miſdeedes. Helpe me, O God my ſauioure for the glorye of thy name: O delyuer and forgeue me my ſynnes for thy riche mercies ſake.</p>
            <p>Remember not the offences of my youth (O Lorde) but thinke vppon thy great mercies and couenaunt, made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p>O moſt merciful father conſider mine infirmities, which are many and great,
<pb facs="tcp:16024:49"/>and beare myne imperfection for thy ſonne my Sauiour Ieſus Chriſtes ſake, which had good erperience of our infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, that he might be merciful vnto al them that are tempted: conſider how the ennemye hath gotten an open way into my fleſhe, wherein I confeſſe that there dwelleth nothynge but ſynne wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and miſerie. Therefore I come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee (O Lord my God) deſiringe thee for Chriſtes ſake, to renewe in mee a right ſpirite, that I may receaue ſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gth and hablenes to do thy wyll, and to ſtande againſte all the aſſaultes of the deuill, that they maye haue no place in me, but that the olde man which I bear about in my body, may be crucified, and dayly dye in me, that the luſtes of ſynne maye vtterly be deſtroyed, that I maye euermore be renewed in the ſpyrite of my minde: that the lyfe of Chriſt may alwayes appeare in me.</p>
            <p>Good lord deliuer me from all kyndes of euyll, as fornycation, couetouſenes, malyciouſnes, enuy, murder, debate, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyte, from whiſperynge, backbitinge, contempt of the &amp; my neyghbour, good lord deliuer me, from euyll ieloſie, from
<pb facs="tcp:16024:49"/>doinge of wronge, pride, boaſting, from adultery, vaine glory, hipocriſie, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonnes, ydolatry, witchecrafte, hatred variaunce, zeale, wrath, ſtrife, ſeditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſectes, enuying, drunkennes, gluttony, and other ſuche lyke.</p>
            <p>Good lord for thy great mercies ſake, deliuer me and graunt me grace to haue thee alwaies before myne eyes, that I may alſo haue a reſpect vnto thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, that whatſoeuer I ſay, thincke or do, may be agreable to thy holy word, that I be not mynded as the vngodlye &amp; wycked men are. Let me haue no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in ſuch thinges as pleaſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: make me lowe in mine owne ſighte (O lorde) that pryde &amp; ſelfe loue ouertake me not. Let not the hand of the vngodly caſt me downe, but bowe my harte alwaies vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, that I may ſerue thee withoute feare all the daies of my lyfe in ſuch ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and righteouſeneſſe, as is accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table before thee. Remoue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me al va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities and lies, take fro me the iuſtes of the bodye, let not the deſires of vnclen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes take holde vppon me, and geue me not ouer vnto an vnſhamefaſt or obſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
<pb facs="tcp:16024:50"/>minde, but holde me alwayes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thy nurture and correction. Of thy fatherly mercy leaue me not to my ſelf, but ſtand thou alwaies by me: for I am to weake of myne owne power to do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thinge that is good, but my ryghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſeneſſe &amp; ſtrength lyeth onely in thee. Therfore (O lord) I come vnto thee, re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quirynge mercy in thy ſight, and the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of thy grace, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I may be ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened with power in the inwarde ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; be armed with thy holy armour, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is the breſtplate of ryghteouſenes, the ſhylde of Fayth, the hope of ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for an helmet, and the ſworde of the ſpirite, whiche is thy holy worde, that I may ſtand parfecte in al that is thy wil, and be founde worthy through Chryſt, to receyue a crowne of lyfe whiche thou haſt promiſed to all them that loue thee in pureneſſe of mynde.</p>
            <p>O Lord plant in me true obedience to thy holy lawe &amp; let not the cares of this world choke thi word in me. Kepe me al ſo from all deſceitefulnes of richeſſe and vncleane deſyres, that all vertues maye be planted in me. Good Lorde geue me grace to walke before thee all the dayes
<pb facs="tcp:16024:50"/>of thys my Pilgrimage with good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and pure minde, that when thou ſhalt appeare to rewarde euery man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to hys dedes, I may reioyce and not be aſhamed of the at thy comming.</p>
            <p>Increaſe my faith (O Lorde my ſauy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our) in thee and in thy Chriſt. Increaſe my loue (O my Redemer) to thee, and to thy ryghteous people. Increaſe a ſure hope in me of my ſaluation, O my Iuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifier. Increaſe ſtrength in me to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſynne, and to ſtande agaynſte all euil temptacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s that they haue no place in me. Encreaſe in me true vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and pure iudgement in thy worde, that I be not deceaued and caryed away in the errour of the wicked: But grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te (O lord) that I may grow in thy grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord &amp; Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſt. Let thy kingdome come vnto me, whiche is righteouſnes, peace, and ioye in thy holy ghoſt, longe ſufferyng, gentlenes, goodnes, faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, mekenes, temperaunce, ſtrength, &amp; pacience, with all ſuche like vertues as ar preſcribed vnto me in thy holy word, that in proſperous thinges I may geue thee thankes, and in aduerſitie be paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent:
<pb facs="tcp:16024:51"/>that I be not lifted vp with the one nor oppreſſed with the other. Oh let al worldly things be vile vnto me for thee. Let me not be mery with the ioy that is without thee, and let me deſire nothing beſide thee. Make me to lift vp my hart oftentimes to thee, and if I chaunce to fall or ſlip, make me to thincke on thee, and be ſory with a ſtedfaſt purpoſe of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendmente. O Lorde I gene ouer my ſelfe into thy holy hande, deſiryng thee for Chriſtes ſake, that I maye remayne vnder thy mighty protection and ſtrong defence of thy power, and that thy holy aungel may alway pitch his tent rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de about me, and compaſſe me alwaies. Good lorde geue me ioyfulnes of harte, and peace of conſcience, continual glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and conſolation in thy worde &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, that I may euermore be thancke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto thee, and prayſe thy name for euer.</p>
            <p>O Lorde thinke vpon all thy people, which are ſtraied here and ther from the fartheſt part of the earthe, which be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into couenaunte with thee, and are minded to walke after thy will, graunt (Oh lorde) that we may grow together
<pb facs="tcp:16024:51"/>in loue throughe the knoweledge of thy worde to keepe the vnitie of the ſpirite, through the bonde of peace, to the vtter confounding of erroure and al falſe opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and to kepe vs cleane from hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryſy and ſuperſtycyon, and to make vs ſtronge in perſecution. We beſech thee fauourably to heare vs good Lorde, and graunt our requeſtes. Geue prayſe to god.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>¶ A Prayer for the forgeuenes of our fynnes and auoydinge of the plague due and at hand for the ſame.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Lorde moſt mighty and feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful God, to all them that hate thee and followe theyr owne waies, and ſeke not to doe thy holy wil, we thy poore creatures, which labour &amp; do deſire to do thy wyl, do ſe by thy righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of thy word, thy fyerce wrath and terrible indignation readye to fall vpon thys realme of Englande, for deſpiſing of thy Preachers and Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſangers, and for the vnthanckful recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, yea treading vnderfote of thy moſt
<pb facs="tcp:16024:52"/>holy word. Vnworthy were we of ſuch a iewell, therfore worthely was it take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away from vs, &amp; leſſe worthy were wee to haue it reſtored to vs agayn, but now leaſt worthy of al ar we to injoy the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite therof. And now we ſe thy wrath is kyndled (O Lorde,) who ſhall be able to quenche it? For our partes we do con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſe that we be worthy of al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> plagues that thou haſte deuiſed agaynſte vs: yet neuertheleſſe we beſech thee vnworthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye to be called thy chyldren: looke not vpon oure deſertes or worthyneſſe, but vpon thy Chryſt &amp; thy fauourable mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, which thou haddeſt in the olde tyme vpon thy chyldren of Iſraell if they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented and turned vnto thee. O Lorde thou diddeſt preſerue them, &amp; kepe them from captiuitie of al other nations, and dyddeſt euer prouide them a faythful go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour or ruler. And furthermore moſt merciful father, although they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed for their wickednes, and left but a ſmall people: yet neuertheleſſe when they tourned vnfaynedly to thee, thou e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer gaueſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the victory ouer all their enemies, ſo that they might dwel as bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>therne together peaceably in their own
<pb facs="tcp:16024:52"/>lande whiche thou gaueſte them. Thou art the ſame lorde and thy mercy endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for euer. And nowe (O lorde) we that ſeke to do thy wil being but a ſmal people, do beſeche the of thy great mercie for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake our only Peace maker, to tourne away thy great wrath and terrible indignatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which we haue deſerued in this realme of Englande, &amp; ſhewe thy compaſſion vpon vs (as thou dyddeſt vppon the children of Iſraell in the olde time) though not for our ſakes whiche haue ſoo wyckedly deſerued thy wrath, but for thy moſt mighty and glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryous names ſake. For if thou ſhuldeſt deſtroy vs and bringe vs vnto deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as we haue deſerued, than ſhuld thy moſte mighty name and thy holy worde be euyll ſpoken of, through vs in al the worlde. Therfore we beſeche thee moſt mercifull father to chaſten and correcte vs, not as we haue deſerued, but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to thy fauourable mercy: not in thy furie, but with thy fatherly pitis: &amp; delyuer vs not ouer into the handes of our ennemies, neyther take thy holye worde from vs O lorde, thoughe of all other we do moſte deſerue it, and haue
<pb facs="tcp:16024:53"/>moſte vnreuerently and vnthanckeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abuſed the ſame. And here we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe vnto thee all oure iniquities, the which are more in numbre the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of our heades, and they preſſe vs ſo downe, that our hartes fayle vs and we dare ſcarſely preſume vnto thee: yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe through Chriſt which is our righteouſnes &amp; hath pacified thy wrath, we are bold to come vnto thee (O lord) being ſory for our faultes euen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our very hartes, deſyring thee for his death and paſſion ſake, to forgeue vs all our ſynnes that euer we haue committed ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in thought, worde, or dede. O lord, we geue ouer oure ſelues into thy holy hands, &amp; with al our hartes do deſyre to doe what ſo euer thy good wyll is that wee ſhoulde doe, beſechinge thee, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt vs with the grace of thy holy ſpirit, that we henſeforth may liue accordyng to that thy moſt godly and bleſſed wyll, and laboure and ſtudye to ſerue thee in newenes of lyfe, taking vppe thy croſſe &amp; folowing thy ſteppes (O lord Chriſte) willingly &amp; cherefully al the days of our lyfe. And furthermore (O lord) we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche thee to geue vs grace to be alway
<pb facs="tcp:16024:53"/>tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kefull both in hart &amp; in our conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation &amp; lyuynge, for al the great bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites that we haue receiued at thy hand, ſo that we maye enioy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to thy glory, and our comforte: euen as at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente we render vnto thee moſte humble thanckes, fyrſte for thy goodnes in the worke of our creation: ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly for that, when we were fallen into euerlaſtinge deſtruction through our conſentynge to the ſubtilte of the ennemie, thou of thy great mercy through Ieſus chriſte didſt raiſe vs vp agayn: &amp; thirdly that it hath pleaſed thee to ſuffer thy holy word, the foode of our ſowles, to haue fre paſſage ones agayne amongeſt vs, and haſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs an harte and a wyl to ſeeke it, to beleue it, and to followe it in our liuing and conuerſation.</p>
            <p>Moreouer we render vnto thee moſte harty thanckes (O heauenly father) for Elyzabeth oure gracious Queene and Gouernoure, whom in muche mercye thou dyddeſt delyuer with thy myghtye arme from the handes of her ennemyes and from the lyons mouthe, and we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche thee ſo to worke in her harte, that of a thankefulnes towards thee for this
<pb facs="tcp:16024:54"/>her great deliueraunce, and thy ſynccu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler bleſſing, conſideryng whoſe miniſter ſhe is, ſhe may ſincerly ſeke and zelouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly promote thy true honour and glorye, buylde vppe thy houſe, confounde thy ſworne aduerſaries, and carefully tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell to brynge thy people committed to her charge, remaynyng yet almoſt in al partes of this realme either in myſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble blyndenes and darke ignoraunce, or wylfully &amp; ſtubbernly kickynge againſt the pricke, to the true knowledge of the and thy bleſſed word. Make all that are in auctoritie vnder her vpryght &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in their callyng, fauourers and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers of thy holy goſpell, followers &amp; practiſers therof, mainteyners and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders of the Preachers and myniſters of the ſame, and ſuche as in ſyngleneſſe of heart wyll ſeeke, not them ſelues but the commoditie of thy people: &amp; graunt that we maye all liue as faythefull ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, in al godly &amp; due obedience, firſte to the Quene as ſupreme head and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour, and then to al other, according to their degree and callynge.</p>
            <p>Fynally we beſeche thee O lorde, that we maye altogether bothe highe &amp; lowe
<pb facs="tcp:16024:54"/>walke in a lyfe and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſation worthy for our profeſſion, to thy glory the good exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of other, and the ſtopping of the mouthes of thy ennemies and oures for thy truthes ſake, that where as they ſla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der vs as euyll doers they maye ſee our good workes &amp; prayſe the in thee day of viſitation. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>¶ A prayer neceſſary to be ſayde at all tymes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Bountiful Ieſu, O ſwete Sauioure, O Chriſte the Sonne of god, haue pitie vpon me, mercifully here me &amp; deſpyſe not my pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. Thou haſte created me of nothynge, thou haſte redemed me from the bondage of ſynne, deathe, and Hell, neyther with Golde nor Siluer, but with thy moſte precious bodye once offered vpon the croſſe, and thyne owne blood ſhed once for al, for my raunſome. Therfore caſt me not away, whom thou by thy great wiſdome haſt made, deſpiſe me not whome thou haſt redemed with ſuche a precious treaſure. Nor lette my
<pb facs="tcp:16024:55"/>wickednes deſtroye that which thy good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes hath builded. Nowe whiles I liue, O Ieſu haue mercy on me: for if I dye oute of thy fauour, it wyll be to late af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde to call for thy mercy. Whiles I haue time to repente, looke vppon me with thy mercifull eies, as thou dyddeſt vouchſafe to looke vpon Peter thyne A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, that I maye bewayle my ſynfull life, and obtaine thy fauour and die ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. I acknowledge that if thou ſhuldeſt deale with me according to thy Iuſtice, I haue deſerued euerlaſtynge deathe.</p>
            <p>Therfore I appeale to thy high throne of mercy, truſting to obtaine thy fauour not for my merites, but for thy merites (O Ieſu) who haſt geuen thy ſelf an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable ſacrifics to thy father to pleaſe his wrath, and to bryng al ſinners true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye repenting and amendinge their euil life, vnto his fauour agayne. Accept me (O Lorde) among the number of theym that ſhall be ſaued, forgeue me my ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, geue me grace to leade a godly and innocent life, graunte me thy heauenlys wiſedome, inſpire my hart with Faith, Hope and Charity, geue me grace to be humble in proſperitie, pacient in aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie
<pb facs="tcp:16024:55"/>obedient to my rulers, faithful vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theym that truſte me, dealing truclye with all men, to lyue chaſtlye in wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke, to abhorre adulterye, fornication and all vncleanes, to doo good after my power vnto al menne, to hurte no man that thy name mays be glorified in me duringe this preſent lyfe, &amp; that I after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde maye attayne euerlaſtinge lyfe, through thy mercye and the merites of thy greuous Paſſion. Amen</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>¶ A Prayer for true mortification and quietnes of the harte in God.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſte bleſſed Lorde Ieſu, graunt me thy grace that it maye be alwaye wyth mee, woorke in me and perſeuere with me vnto the ende, and that I maye euer deſire and will that is moſt pleaſaunt and moſte acceptable to thee: thy will be my will, and my will alway to followe thy will: be there al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in me one will and one deſire with thee, ſo that I maye haue noo power to wil or not to wil, but euen as thou wilt or wilt not, and graunt me that I may
<pb facs="tcp:16024:56"/>dye to all thinges that be in the world, and for thee to loue &amp; be glad to be dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſed, and to be as a man vnknowen to this worlde. Graunt me alſo, aboue al that can be deſired, that I may reſte me in thee, and fully in thee may pacify my hearte: for thou lorde art the very true peace of harte, and the perfect reſte both of body and ſoule, and without thee all thinges be greuous and vnquiet. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore let my hart finde peace and comfort in that peace y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is in thee on highe, one bleſſed and one endleſſe goodnes, &amp; reſte therin for euermore. So be it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>¶ A prayer to be ſayd before the hearing or readynge of goddes word.</head>
            <p>ALmighty God and moſt mercifull father, whoſe word is a lanterne to our fete and a lighte vnto oure ſteppes, we moſt humblye beſech thee to illuminate our mindes, that we may vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtand the myſteries conteyned in thy holy lawe, and into the ſelfe ſame thing that we godly vnderſtande, we maye be vertuouſely tranſeformed, ſo that of no parte wee offende thy dyuine maieſtye, through our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:56"/>
            <head>An prayer for remiſſion of ſynnes.</head>
            <p>WHen we loke backe and behold our ſinfull life paſte (O Lorde) what a du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geon of errours, vice, and wickednes openeth it ſelfe vnto vs? ſo that ther is no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but he muſt nedes be aſhamed of him ſelf, when he calleth to mind what he hath bene: and tremble when he conſidereth the wickednes and ſinfull courſe of his lyfe to come. For who ſhall vndertake that the reſt of our lyfe ſhalbe any better then that is paſt? howe can we then ſufficiently magnifie and prayſe thy great mercy which haſte differred thy puniſhement ſo longe? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdynge therfore this our daungerous &amp; miſerable ſtate, we come vnto thee (O thou great &amp; mighty iudge) in tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blyng &amp; feare, hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly beſechig thee not to heape vpon vs thy deſerued ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geaunce, but let thy tender kyndneſſe and loue thou bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to Ieſus chriſt thy dere ſon our gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious lorde &amp; redemer, couer our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: for whoſe ſake (though we deſerue al extremitie) thou doeſt pardon vs.</p>
            <p>If thou lord ſhalt ſtraitly marke our iniquities (O lord) who ſhalbe hable to abide it?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:57"/>
            <head>A prayer againſt our ſpiritual enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, the deuyll, the worlde, and the fleſhe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lorde god, the deuyl go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth about lyke a roaryng lyon ſekyng who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he may deuoure, the fleſhe luſteth agaynſte the ſpirits, the worlde perſwadeth vnto vanities, that we maye forget thee our Lorde God and ſo for euer be dampned. Thus are we miſerablye on euery ſyde beſet and beſieged of cruell and vnreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ennemies, and lyke at euery mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to periſh if we be not defended with thy godly power agaynſte theyr tyranny. We therfore poore &amp; wretched ſynners, diſpayring of our owne ſtrength (which in dede is none) moſt hartely praye thee to endue vs with ſtrength from aboue that we may be hable through thy helpe with ſtronge faith to reſiſt Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with feruent prayer to mortifie the luſtes of the fleſhe, with continual meditation of thy holy lawe to auoyd the foolyſhe va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities and tranſitorye pleaſures of this wicked worlde: that through thy grace
<pb facs="tcp:16024:57"/>beinge ſet at lybertie from the power of theſe our mortall ennemies, maye lyue and ſerue thee in holyneſſe and ryghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe al the dayes of our lyfe. worke this in vs O holy and bleſſed ſpirite, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Father &amp; the ſonne one true and euerliuing god, ful of maieſtie and power, whiche with thy heauenlye inſpirations quickeneſte the myndes of them that afore were dead in ſinne, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt ioyful the hartes of the faythful pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent, bringeſt into the waye of truthe al ſuche as haue erred and gone aſtray, comforteſt the ſowles of them that hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and thyrſt after ryghteouſneſſe, and plenteouſly enrycheſt thoſe with diuerſe gyftes which aſke them in Ieſus Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes name: purifie our hartes we beſech thee, inflame them with the fyre of thy loue, arme vs againſt the crafty aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of ſubtyl ſathan, agaynſt the vayne plcſures of the wicked world, &amp; agaynſt the ſinfull luſtes of fylthy fleſhe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we beynge endued with grace from aboue by thy holy inſpiration, may walke for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes in neweneſſe of lyfe, in true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes and righteouſnes all the dayes of our lyfe. Fyl our hartes with newe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes
<pb facs="tcp:16024:58"/>and ſpirituall motions, &amp; renewe vs both in body and ſowle that we may dye vnto olde Adam; &amp; lyue vnto righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſenes through a liuely faythe whiche worketh by Charitie: whiche ſynguler gyfte of faythe graunt vnto vs, that we truely beleuing in thee (O eternal God the father the ſonne and the holy ghoſt) and fully perſwaded of the truthe of thy holy word, may be made thy ſonnes and inheritours of the euerlaſtynge ioyes: whiche as they are great and vnſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, ſo are there fewe that do inioy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For ſtraite is the way &amp; narrowe is the gate that leadeth therunto, &amp; fewe there be that fynde it. Notwithſtandinge O god thou haſt a lyttell flocke, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is thy pleaſure to geue that ioyful king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, whoſe names are wrytten in the boke of lyfe. Make vs therfore of that nombre (for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake) &amp; place vs amongeſt thoſe thy ſhepe whiche ſhall ſtande on thy ryght hande to receiue that bleſſed inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytance and dwell with thee for euermore.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:58"/>
            <head>An other prayer.</head>
            <p>REme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre not O lorde god our olde iniquites, but let thy mercy ſpede<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly preuent vs, for we be very my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable: help vs god our ſauiour, and for the glory of thy name deliuer vs, be mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciful &amp; forgeue our ſynnes. Let not the wicked people ſaye, where is their god? we be thy people &amp; the ſhepe of thy paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, we ſhal geue tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes vnto thee for euer: fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> age to age we ſhal ſet forth thy lawde and praiſe: to thee be honour and glory world without ende. Amen.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Peter.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>The day of the Lord will come as a theefe in the night, in the which day the heauens ſhall peryſhe with ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible noiſe, and the Elementes ſhall melt with heate, and the earth with the worckes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are therin ſhal burne vp. Seinge therfore that all theſe things ſhall periſh, what maner per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons oughte ye to be in holy conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacion and godlines, loking for and haſtening vnto the day of God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:59"/>
            <head>¶ The Letany and ſuffrages.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> GOD the father of heauen: haue mercye vppon vs myſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſinners.</p>
            <p>O God the father. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>O god the Son redemer of the worlde: haue mercy vpon vs myſerable ſinners.</p>
            <p>O God the ſonne redemer. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>O God the holy ghoſte procedinge from the father, and the ſonne: haue mercye vpon vs myſerable ſinners.</p>
            <p>O God the holy ghoſt. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>O holy, bleſſed, and glorious Trinitie, three perſons and one god: haue mercye vpon vs miſerable ſinners.</p>
            <p>O holye, bleſſed, and glorious. &amp;c. Remember not Lorde oure offences nor the offences of oure forefathers, neyther take thou vengeaunce of oure ſynnes: Spare vs good Lorde, ſpare thy people whom thou haſt redemed wyth thy moſt precious bludde, and be not angry with vs for euer.</p>
            <p>Spare vs good lorde.</p>
            <p>From all euyl and miſchiefe, from ſyn, from the craftes &amp; aſſaultes of the deuil, from thy wrathe and from euerlaſtynge
<pb facs="tcp:16024:59"/>dampnation.</p>
            <p>Good lorde deliuer vs.</p>
            <p>From all blindnes of hart, from pryde, vayne glorye and hipocriſie, from enuie hatred and malice, and al vncharitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</p>
            <p>Good Lorde deliuer vs.</p>
            <p>From Fornication, and al other deadly ſynne, and from al the deceyptes of the world, the fleſhe, and the deuyl.</p>
            <p>Good Lorde deliuer vs.</p>
            <p>From lightnynge and tempeſte, from plague peſtilence and famine, from bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel and murder, and from ſodain death.</p>
            <p>Good Lorde deliuer vs.</p>
            <p>From al ſedicion and priuie conſpiracy, from all falſe doctrine and hereſy, from hardnes of harte, and contempte of thy worde and commaundement.</p>
            <p>Good Lorde deliuer vs.</p>
            <p>By the miſtery of thy holy incarnacion, by thy holy natiuitie and circumſition, by thy baptiſme faſting, and temptacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>Good Lorde deliuer.</p>
            <p>By thyne agony and blouddy ſweat, by thy Croſſe and Paſſion, by thy precious death and burial, by thy glorious reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and aſcention, and by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng
<pb facs="tcp:16024:60"/>of the holy ghoſt.</p>
            <p>Good Lorde deliuer vs.</p>
            <p>In al time of our tribulation, in al time of our wealth, in the houre of death, and in the day of iudgement.</p>
            <p>Good Lorde deliuer vs.</p>
            <p>We ſynners do beſeche thee to heare vs (O Lorde God) &amp; that it may pleaſe the to rule and gouerne thy holy churche v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſally in the right waye.</p>
            <p>We beſeche thee to heare vs. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That it maye pleaſe thee to keepe and ſtrengthen in the true worſhippinge of thee, in ryghteouſnes and bolines of life thy ſeruaunt Elizabeth our moſt gracy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Queene and gouernour.</p>
            <p>We beſech thee to heare vs. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That it may pleaſe the to rule her hart in thy faythe, feare, and loue, and that ſhe may euermore haue affiaunce in thee and euer ſeke thy honour and glorye.</p>
            <p>We beſech thee to heare vs. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That it may pleaſe thee to be her defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and keper geuing her the victory o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all her enemies.</p>
            <p>We beſech thee to heare vs. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That it maye pleaſe thee to illuminate all Byſhoppes Paſtours and miniſters
<pb facs="tcp:16024:60"/>of the church with trew knowledge and vnderſtandyng of thy woorde, and that both by theyr preachynge and lyuinge, they maye ſet it foorth and ſhewe it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynglye.</p>
            <p>We beſech thee to heare vs. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That it maye pleaſe thee to endue the lordes of the counſell, and all the nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litye, with grace, wiſedome, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge.</p>
            <p>We beſech thee to heare vs. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That it may pleaſe thee to bleſſe &amp; kepe the Magiſtrates, geuyng them grace to execute iuſtice and to mainteine truth.</p>
            <p>We beſech thee to heare vs. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That it maye pleaſe thee to bleſſe and keepe all thy people.</p>
            <p>We beſech thee to heare vs. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That it maye pleaſe thee to geue to all nacions, vnitie, peace, and concorde.</p>
            <p>We beſech thee to heare vs. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That it maye pleaſe thee to geue vs an harte to loue and dreade thee, and dily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentlye to lyue after thy commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes.</p>
            <p>We beſech thee to heare vs. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That it maye pleaſe thee to geue al thy people increaſe of grace to heare meke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:16024:61"/>thy word, and to receyue it with pure affection and to bryng forthe the fruites of the ſpiryte.</p>
            <p>We beſech thee to heare vs. &amp;c. That it may pleaſe thee to brynge into the waye of truth all ſuch as haue erred and are deceyued.</p>
            <p>We beſech thee to heare vs. &amp;c. That it maye pleaſe thee to ſtrengthen ſuche as do ſtande, and to comforte and helpe the weake hearted, and to raiſe vp the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that fal, and finally to beate downe Sathan vnder our fete.</p>
            <p>We beſech thee to heare vs. &amp;c. That it maye pleaſe thee to ſuccoure, helpe, and comforte all that be in daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, neceſſitie and tribulacion.</p>
            <p>We beſech thee to heare vs. &amp;c. That it maye pleaſe thee to preſerue all that trauayle by lande or by water, all women labouryng of chyld, al ſicke per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and younge chyldren and to ſhewe thy pytie vpon all pryſoners &amp; captiues.</p>
            <p>We beſech thee to heare vs. &amp;c. That it maye pleaſe thee to defend, and prouyde for the fatherles chyldren and wydowes, and all that be deſolate and oppreſſed</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:61"/>
            <p>We beſech thee to heare vs. &amp;c. That it maye pleaſe thee to haue mercy vpon all men.</p>
            <p>We beſech thee to heare vs. &amp;c. That it maye pleaſe thee to forgeue our enemies, perſecutours and ſlaunderers, and to tourne their hartes.</p>
            <p>We beſech thee to heare vs. &amp;c. That it may pleaſe thee to giue and pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerue to our vſe the kindly fruites of the earth, ſo as in due tyme we maye enioy them.</p>
            <p>We beſech thee to heare vs. &amp;c. That it may pleaſe thee to gyue vs true repentaunce, to forgeue vs all oure ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, negligences, and ignoraunces, and to endue vs with the grace of thy holye ſpirite, to amend our lyues accordyng to thy holy worde.</p>
            <p>We beſech thee to heare vs. &amp;c. Sonne of God, we beſeche thee to heare vs.</p>
            <p>Sonne of god we beſech. &amp;c. O Lambe of God that takeſt awaye the ſynnes of the world.</p>
            <p>Graunt vs thy peace.</p>
            <p>O Lambe of God, that takeſt away the ſinnes of the world.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:62"/>
            <p>Haue mercy vpon vs.</p>
            <p>O Chriſt heare vs.</p>
            <p>O Chriſt heare vs.</p>
            <p>Lord haue mercy vpon vs.</p>
            <p>Chriſt haue mercy vpon vs.</p>
            <p>Chriſt haue mercy vpon vs.</p>
            <p>Lorde haue mercy vpon vs.</p>
            <p>Lorde haue mercy vpon vs.</p>
            <p>Our father which art. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And leade vs not into temptation.</p>
            <p>But deliuer vs from euil. Amen.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The verſicle.</head>
               <p>O Lorde deale not with vs after our ſinnes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Aunſwere.</head>
               <p>Neither reward vs after our iniquities.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>Let vs praye.</opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> God mercifull father, that deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſeſt not the ſighing of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite hart, nor the deſire of ſuch as be ſorowfull, mercifully aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyſte oure prayers that we make before thee in all our troubles and aduerſities when ſo euer they oppreſſe vs, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſely heare vs, that thoſe euils whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the craft and ſubtilty of the deuill or man worketh againſt vs, be brought to
<pb facs="tcp:16024:62"/>naughte, and by the prouidence of thy goodnes they may be diſperied, that we thy ſeruantes being hurt by no perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, maye euermore geue thankes vnto thee in thy holy church thorough Ieſus Chriſt our lorde. Amen.</p>
               <p>O Lord ariſe, helpe vs, and deliuer vs for thy names ſake.</p>
               <p>O God we haue heard with our eares, and oure fathers haue declared vnto vs the noble works that thou didſt in theyr dayes, and in the olde time before them.</p>
               <p>O Lord ariſe, helpe vs, and deliuer vs for thy honour.</p>
               <p>Glory be to the father. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>As it was in the beginnyng. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ennemies defend vs, O Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Graciouſly looke vppon our afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>Pitifullye beholde the ſorowes of oure harte.</p>
               <p>Mercifullye forgeue the ſynnes of thy people.</p>
               <p>Fauourably with mercy heare our pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers.</p>
               <p>O ſonne of Dauid haue mercy vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs.</p>
               <p>Both now and euer vouchſafe to heare
<pb facs="tcp:16024:63"/>vs, O Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Graciouſly heare vs, O Chriſt, gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciouſly heare vs, O Lord Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Verſicle.</head>
               <p>O Lorde let thy mercye be ſhewed vpon vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Aunſwere</head>
               <p>As we do put our truſt in thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>Let vs praye.</opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E humblye beſeche thee (O father) mercyfully to looke vpon oure infirmities, and for the glorye of thy names ſake, turne from vs all thoſe euyls, that we moſt righteouſly haue deſerued. And graunte that in al our troubles we may put oure whole truſte and confidence in thy mercye and euermore ſerue thee in holynes and purenes of liuinge, to thy honoure and glory through our onelye mediatour and aduocate Ieſus Chriſte our Lorde. Amen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>¶ A prayer for the Queenes Maieſtie.</head>
            <p>O Lord our heauenly Father, high &amp; mightye, Kyng of Kynges, Lorde
<pb facs="tcp:16024:63"/>of Lordes, the onely Ruler of Prynces, which doeſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy throne behold al the dwellers vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth: moſt hartely we beſech thee, wyth thy fauour to beholde our mooſte gracyous Souerayne Ladye Queene Elizabeth, and ſo repleniſhe her with the grace of thy holye ſpyrite, that ſhe may alwaye inclyne to thy wyll, and walke in thy way. Indue her plentifully with heauenlye gyftes: Graunte her in health and welth long to lyue, ſtrength her that ſhee maye vanquiſhe and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all her enemyes. And finally after thys lyfe, ſhe maye attaine euerlaſtinge ioy and felicitie. Through Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>¶ A prayer for paſtours and myniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Church.</head>
            <p>ALmyghty and euerlaſtinge God, which onely woorkeſt great mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailes, ſende downe vppon oure Paſtours, and Myniſters and al congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacions committed to their charge, the healthfull ſpiryte of thy grace, and that they may truely pleaſe thee: Powre vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them the continuall due of thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing: Graunte thys (O Lorde) for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure
<pb facs="tcp:16024:64"/>of oure aduocate and mediatoure Ieſus Chryſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>¶ For rayne yf the time require.</head>
            <p>O God, heauenly Father, which by thy Sonne Ieſus Chriſt haſt promyſed to all them that ſeke thy kyngdome, &amp; the righteouſnes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, all thynges neceſſary to theyr bodily ſuſtenaunce: Sende vs we beſeche thee, in this oure neceſſitye, ſuche moderate raine and ſhewres, that we may receaue the fruites of the earth to our comforte, &amp; to thy honoure, through Ieſus Chriſte our Lord. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>¶ For faire weather.</head>
            <p>O Lorde God, which for the ſynne of man dyddeſte once drowne all the worlde excepte. viii. perſons, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde of thy greate mercye diddeſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe neuer to deſtroye it ſo agayne: wee humblye beſeche thee that although we for our iniquities: haue worthely deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued this plague of rayne &amp; waters, yet vppon oure true repentaunce thou wilt
<pb facs="tcp:16024:64"/>ſende vs ſuche weather, wherby we may receyue the fruictes of the earth in due ſeaſon, and learne both by thy punyſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente to amende oure liues, and for thy clemency to geue thee prayſe and glory, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>¶ In the time of dearth and famine.</head>
            <p>O God heauenlye father, whoſe gifte it is that the rayne dooeth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fal, the earth is fruitful, beaſtes encreaſe, and fyſhes do multyplye: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, we beſech thee, the afflyctions of thy people, and graunt that the ſcarcitie and derth (which we do now moſt iuſtly ſuffer for oure iniquitie) maye throughe thy goodnes be mercifullie tourned into cheapenes and plentye, for the loue of Ieſus Chriſt oure lord, to whome wyth thee and the holye ghoſte, be prayſe for euer. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>¶ In the time of warre.</head>
            <p>O Almightie GOD, kinge of al Kynges and gouernoure of all thinges, whoſe power no crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb facs="tcp:16024:65"/>is able to reſiſte, to whom it belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth iuſtly to punyſh ſynners, and to be merciful vnto them that truelye repent: Saue and deliuer vs (we humbly beſech thee) from the handes of our enemies, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate theyr pryde, aſſwage their malyce, and confounde theyr deuiſes, that we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge armed wyth thy defence maye be preſerued euermore from all perylles to glorify thee, which art y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only giuer of al victory through the merytes of thy one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſonne: Ieſus Chriſt our lord. Amen</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>¶ A praier of Chriſoſtome.</head>
            <p>ALmyghty God which haſt geuen vs grace at this time with one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde to make oure common ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plycations vnto thee, and doeſt promyſe that when two or thre be gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther in thy name, thou wilt graunt their requeſtes: fulfyl now O lord the deſires and peticions of thy ſeruauntes as may be moſte expedient for them grauntinge vs in thys worlde knoweledge of thy trueth, and in the worlde to come life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtinge. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16024:65"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
